<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The [H]istory of the [l]ife and death [of] that antient father of the church, [D]r. Joh. Thauler [who] lived at Colen [sic] in Germany in the year of [Ou]r Lord, 1346, where he was in a [m]iraculous manner turned from his vain conversation to an extraordinary degree [of] holiness of life : [toge]ther with many of his precepts ... / [f]aithfully translated out of Latine.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 203 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86400</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2167A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43640</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475048</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475048</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151173</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86400)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151173)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2248:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The [H]istory of the [l]ife and death [of] that antient father of the church, [D]r. Joh. Thauler [who] lived at Colen [sic] in Germany in the year of [Ou]r Lord, 1346, where he was in a [m]iraculous manner turned from his vain conversation to an extraordinary degree [of] holiness of life : [toge]ther with many of his precepts ... / [f]aithfully translated out of Latine.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 158 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[P]rinted for Lodowick Lloyd, and are to be [sold at hi]s Shop at the Castle in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: torn, stained, and tightly bound; bracketed material lacking from t.p., partially supplied from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tauler, Johannes, ca. 1300-1361.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151173:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ISTORY OF THE <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>IFE and DEATH <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that Antient Father of the Church, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Joh. Thauler, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lived at <hi>Colen</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> in the year of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>r Lord, 1346. where he was in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iraculous manner turned from his vain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onverſation to an extraordinary degree <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f holineſs of life. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ther, with many of his Precepts, Poſitions, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ermons; but eſpecially the Means and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>r how he came to be ſo highly Illuminated, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d to the underſtanding of the ſecret Myſteries <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Goſpel, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aithfully Tranſlated out of Latine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rinted for <hi>Lodowick Lloyd,</hi> and are to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Shop at the Caſtle in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="narration">
            <pb facs="tcp:151173:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151173:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY Of the Life of the ſublime and illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated Divine, Dr. <hi>John Thauler,</hi> who at <hi>Colin</hi> (where he lived) was in an Extraordinary and Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous manner turned from his vain Converſation to an Extraordinary degree of Sanctity, and Holineſs of Life.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the year of our Lord, One thouſand three hundred forty ſix, there lived a Doctor of Divinity in <hi>Colin</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> a frequent Preacher exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly followed, and famous for his Doctrine far and near. A certain Layman aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly endowed and anointed with Divine Grace, hearing his fame, and being thrice warned in a Dream to go to the City where the Doctor lived, (which was at the leaſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151173:3"/> thirty mile diſtance from the place, where then the Layman was) reſolved with himſelf to Travel thither, and try what it would pleaſe Divine grace to bring to paſs; then he takes his journey, arrives at the City where the Doctor lived; attentively heard him five times Preach; In which while he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in the Spirit, that the Doctor was by nature an ingenuous Man, of a mild, ſweet, and courteous behaviour, and excellently well skilled in the Letter of the Scripture; but obſcurely and glimeringly underſtanding it, being without the Light of Divine grace. The Layman exceedingly hereupon pittying his condition, went to him, and thus entered into diſcourſe with him. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Sir, I am come above thirty miles to ſit at your feet, and hear your Doctrine, drawn by the fame of your excellent abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and already have I heard five of your Sermons; Therefore I beſeech you for Gods ſake vouchſafe while I ſtay here, to be my Confeſſor. The courteous Dr. refuſing not the motion; The Layman oft came to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, which he performed with much ſimplicity and humility: and when ever he thought fit to receive the moſt ſacred Body of our Lord, he received it at the Doctors hands. Twelve weeks in this manner be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151173:3"/> ſpent, the Layman came to the Doctor with a requeſt, which he thus uttered: Reverend Maſter, I beſeech you for Gods ſake teach us in a Sermon the moſt compendious way of attaining the higheſt degree of perfection, that this Life is capable of. What doſt thou mean Son (quoth the Doctor) to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe would it be to Preach ſuch ſublime matters to you, who (I ſuppoſe) would hardly be able to underſtand one word? Though poſſibly (anſwered the Layman) I may not (Reverend Sir) be able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand you, yet at leaſt I ſhall breath and pant after, and with hearty and frequent Prayers deſire thoſe things you ſhall deliver. Beſide, a great multitude of people come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to hear you; now if but one of theſe ſhall rightly underſtand what you ſhall ſay, your labour will not be loſt. I but (ſaid the Doctor) if I ſhould be put upon that you deſire (good Son) it would coſt me firſt much pains and ſtudy, and a great deal of labour, to gather what would be requiſite to the buſineſs, and to digeſt it into fit method. But whatever excuſes the Doctor made, the Layman would not give over his entreaty till the Doctor paſſed his word, that he would Preach ſuch a Sermon as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired. It fell out ſhortly after that the Dr.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151173:4"/> Preach'd in a certain Monaſtry; And Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon being ended; he told the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that thoſe whom other buſineſs hindred not, might reſort thither upon the third day following; for I am deſired (quoth he) to Preach a Sermon, in which I muſt ſhew, by what means one may moſt compendiouſly come to the higheſt degree of perfection at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable in this Life. The third day being come, very many flocked to the place; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, betimes in the morning thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haſtens the Layman, that he might get a convenient place where he might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hear, and underſtand the Doctor. The Doctor comes as he had appointed, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins this following Diſcourſe.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="sermon">
                  <body>
                     <head>In this following moſt excellent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, there are laid down four and twenty points, by which may be known who are truly illuminated men, and true contemplators.</head>
                     <p>SO great &amp; many things (dearly beloved) are to be handled at this time touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Argument, I lately promiſed to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon, that according to my conſtant cuſtome, I cannot take the Goſpel of the day for my Text, nor uſe many Latine words.</p>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:151173:4"/>
                     <p>But notwithſtanding thoſe matters that I ſhall handle, ſhall be ſuch as may be eaſily confirmed out of Scripture.</p>
                     <p>In the firſt place (beloved) I would not have you ignorant, how there are very many to be found, who attain to a clear know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, underſtanding, and a rational decern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Heavenly matters; but it is altogether by Images and Forms in their fancy; impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed there ſometimes by the ſtudy of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſometimes without it. Many of theſe when this ſpeculative Light of their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect by the aforeſaid means; either by the ſtudy of Scripture, or ſome way elſe begins to ſhine, they ſit down in it, abundantly ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; but all ſuch (queſtionleſs) are far enough from the top and higheſt degree of perfection: but if any one ſuch could be found, who had pierced and paſſed through the fore mentioned attainment, and were totally and centrally mortifyed to it, and who had got above all ſorts of Images and Forms in the fancy; Such a one would infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely be more dear and acceptable to God, then an hundred thouſand of the other ſort of men, who live in their own habitual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, and modes, taken up by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, out of ſelf-will, and inſenſible and intelectual Images, ſo totally taken up with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151173:5"/> them, that they take no care to deny and mortifie themſelves. For indeed God is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together hinder'd from entering into and poſſeſſing ſuch, by reaſon of their ſelf will, and their own proper working in their own ſtrength, by which they are detained in their own dearly beloved, and delighted in intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual imaginations. But thoſe that have paſſed through ſuch, and by a kind of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing have reſigned up themſelves to God, and have gone out of all manner of imaginary comtemplations, and finally with humble reſignation, have offer'd and given up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, free and naked, above all intellectual imaginations, (as St. <hi>Dioniſius</hi> ſaith, that the Light of Faith requires, that a man ſhould mount above the utmoſt power and capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of reaſon, or intellect:) ſuch (I ſay) as have come to this ſtate, in them God finds a reſting place, where he may dwell and work all their works in them; when, where, and in what manner he pleaſeth: For when as God ſeeth in them no impediment, he works in them his own work, and doth act and lead them to himſelf, and in himſelf. Such men as theſe are unknown to any; becauſe there lives and converſations are hidden to all, unleſs thoſe that are of the ſame Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, State, or Complection, of which I fear
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151173:5"/> there are very few. But to this heighth and perfection of Life, no man can attain, but by the profoundeſt and deepeſt humility, a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous and pure intellect, and a clear and illuminated reaſon. Although indeed (which cannot be denyed) once many intelligent Spirits which by Nature are nothing elſe but pure intelligences, fowlly erred, and fell from that eternal Unity, and were alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſecluded out of the Chorus of Angels; the ſame thing likewiſe happens every day to ſuch which look upon themſelves with ſelf-pleaſing flattery, and by uſurping ſelf-will, and a vain complacency in their own ſubtilty, make themſelves like thoſe fallen Angels. Wherefore (beloved) it concerns us to know, and to be able to diſtinguiſh, who are truly illuminated and wiſe Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plators. Truely I have found ſo far as may be gathered from Scripture; four and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Particulars which a truly illuminated Man ought to have in him: which Particulars I ſhall willingly deliver at this time, and ſo conclude.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <label>1.</label> The Firſt Particular, even the chief Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of Doctors, and Teacher of all true Wiſdom and Knowledge; Chriſt Jeſus our Lord mentions, where he ſaith, <note place="margin">John 13.</note> 
                           <hi>By this ſhall all men know that you are my Diſciples,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151173:6"/> if you love one the other, and ſhall keep that my Commandement, which I commanded you,</hi> 
                           <note place="margin">John 15.</note> 
                           <hi>that you love one another even as I have loved you;</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ye have all knowledge, and skill, all Miſtery; if there be wanting Fidelity, and Charity, it profiteth nothing. For it is ſaid of <hi>Balaam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>,</hi> that he was endowed with ſo piercing and ſubtile a wit, and reaſon, that he foreſaw thoſe things which God many hundred years afterward brought to paſs, and manifeſted: but this profited him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, becauſe as he ought he did not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in love adhere to the truth known; Thus much ſhall ſuffice for the firſt point.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>2</label> The Second Point is this; namely, That he be free from, and totally delivered from ſelf; which notwithſtanding will never ſeem ſo to him, but rather he will always think that he ought yet more and more to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted of ſelf, and to renounce all things.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>3</label> The Third thing is, That he be deeply and thoroughly reſign'd to God, in ſo much that God may not find in him the leaſt impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but that he may work freely all his works in him, which perfection he will not raſhly aſcribe to himſelf, but will think himſelf of all men fartheſt off from it.</item>
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:151173:6"/>
                        <item>
                           <label>4</label> The Fourth followeth, That he do totally go out of, and deny himſelf, and all thing elſe, in which he hath heretofore inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately loved, ſought or intended himſelf, whether they have been things Temporal or things Eternal.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>5</label> Fifthly, That he ſeek not his own or himſelf in any meaſure; either in himſelf, or any Creature.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>6</label> Sixtly, That he alwayes, and in all places diligently attend, and obſerve what God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of him, and what he would have him to do, and chearfully (relying upon Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace) perform it; and ſatisfie Divine expectation; but not in the leaſt what ever, from thence arrogate to himſelf any thing.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>7</label> Seventlhy, That continually without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion he conform himſelf to Divine Will, ſo as that he will nothing elſe but what God willeth.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>8</label> Eightly, That he would ſo ſtrongly and powerfully work and excerciſe himſelf in God, and by and immence force, ſtrongeſt bands of love ſo bind and unite himſelf to him, that God may not as it were do any thing in himſelf without him, nor he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe perform any thing without God.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>9</label> Ninthly, That in all things which ſhall happen to him, whether they be pleaſant or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151173:7"/> bitter, yea in every work, in every perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, in every place, at all times, he enjoy ſenſibly Divine preſence.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>10</label> Tenthly, That he receive nothing at all whether it be grateful or grievous, as from the hands of any Creature; but all things nakedly and ſimply as from the hands of God. Whatever God ſhall do, or permit to be done by Creatures, he receive it no otherways then as from God himſelf.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>11</label> The Eleventh point is this, That he never ſuffer himſelf to be in any meaſure over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, or taken with a natural delight or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of any Creature, without true and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable neceſſity.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>12</label> The Twelfth point is this, That neither he be to much depreſt or overwhelm'd, nor immoderatly vexed or inwardly grieved, with any whatever adverſity which may happen to him from the truth, but alwayes conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adhere to the truth.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>13</label> The Thirteenth point, That he ſuffer not himſelf to be deceived by any falſe Light, or by any gliſtering ſhew of any Creatures; but chearfully and lovingly leave all things as he found them, making the beſt of every thing, and contending earneſtly to be made the better by every thing, and by nothing to be made worſe.</item>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:151173:7"/>
                        <item>
                           <label>14</label> The Fourteenth point, That he be always upon his guard, ſufficiently provided of, and armed with all ſorts of Vertues to reſiſt all Vices whatſoever, that ſo he may never be otherways then Conquerer, and in all conflicts bear away the Palm of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>15</label> The Fifteenth point, That he nakedly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to underſtand and contemplate (ſo far as God permits, and he be able) truth, as it is in it ſelf, and according to it lead his Life, and ſtudy to ſatisfie and anſwer the known truth in every thing.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>16</label> The Sixteenth point, That he be perfect, juſt and upright, and that he eſteem himſelf nothing leſs than ſo.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>17</label> The Seventeenth point, That he be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in Words, yet full of inward Vigour and Life.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>18</label> The Eighteenth point, That his Life be faithful, retired, humble, which by a good Example rather then Words may Preach to all, and Speak by doing.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>19</label> The Nineteenth point, That he ſuffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf willingly to be overcome by all which contend with him, and that in all things which belong to himſelf, but not in things which concern God.</item>
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:151173:8"/>
                        <item>
                           <label>20</label> The Twentieth point, That above all things he ſeek the Glory of God, and aime at, and intend nothing elſe in all his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>21</label> The Twenty firſt point, That he rejoyce not at all in any Priviledge, which he hath in any thing above others; but that he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together himſelf is unworthy of the leaſt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>22</label> The Twenty ſecond point, That from his Heart he believe himſelf to be one of the moſt unprofitableſt men in the World; yet nevertheleſs, let there be always found in him great Vigour, Faith, Hope and Charity; and let him not at all value his own Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, nor all his works done by humane reaſon.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>23</label> The Twenty third point, That in all his Words and Works he ſet before him as in a Glaſs, the Life and Doctrine of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and that in them he continually contemplate himſelf, and as much as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, renounce, caſt away, and mortifie all whatſoever ſhall be found in him, unlike to the lovely Image of our Saviour.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>24</label> The Twenty fourth and laſt point, That after all, he now as it were firſt begin, like a little Child as yet, to make proficiency in true profound deep and perfect humility, and think no other ways, than that he is now to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151173:8"/> begin to implore Divine benignity, that it would find him out a way and afford aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, whereby he may become a good man. And if he be eſteemed ſo by ſome, or elſe for that cauſe he appear vile and baſe in the eyes of men; even that will be more grateful and acceptable to him, then if he ſhould enjoy the favour and good-will of all.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>But I fear my beloved, leaſt I have been too tedious; Therefore theſe are the ſigns of a rational and purged ground, which the Splendour and beautiful Image of all truth doth enlighten and teach. Let every one therefore look within himſelf, and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſearch, whether he find within himſelf theſe twenty four Points, which if he do let him rejoyce; but if he do not, let him know that his underſtanding, though never ſo lofty and towering, nor all his ſubtile and witty works of his own reaſon, worth a ruſh; for he that is the Fountain &amp; Pattern of all truth, can perform in him no ſupernatural work, unleſs he do prevent him by his ſingular and ſpecial grace, as we read he did to St. <hi>Paul.</hi> But this in my judgment happens very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arly in theſe our times. Finally, let the Eternal Truth our Lord God, grant that we may all be made by his grace, true Contemplators
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151173:9"/> in true and perfect humility, to his Praiſe and Glory.</p>
                     <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>It follows how the <hi>Layman</hi> did in ſecret partly diſcover to the <hi>Doctor</hi> his hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Sanctity, and how he convinced him that he was yet in the night of Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and that his Veſſel was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, and that himſelf was of the number of the <hi>Phariſees.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE fore-written Sermon being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the Layman ſtraight haſtning to his Inne, there Writes it out word for word as it was delivered by the Doctor, comes with his Notes to the Doctor, and ſaid thus to him; Reverend Sir, your Sermon I have writ out fair, and if it be not too troubleſome I will repeat it out of my Paper.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor,</label> Truly I'le very willingly hear it: then the Layman read the whole Sermon, which being done, he ſpake thus to the Doctor.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> I pray Sir tell me if I have omitted any of your Words, that I may write them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Believe it dear Son, you have exactly taken my Sermon word for word, as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151173:9"/> I Preach'd it; and I'le aſſure you might I gain never ſo much I could not again write it ſo exactly and verbatim as you have done, unleſs I would take again the ſame pains which I did in the ſearch of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and I profeſs I cannot now ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admire your happy wit and parts, and that you ſhould ſo oft make your confeſſion to me, and yet I never perceive till now. Then the Layman made as though he would take his leave of the Doctor, and ſaid to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> I entend (Sir) God willing to return home.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Away, away, what is it that ſhould compel you to return home, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you have neither Wife nor Children to take care of; and what hinders, but that, fith you have no body at home, you may as well live here as there. I'le promiſe you ſhortly (God willing) I will Preach ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sermon of the utmoſt perfection of a Spiritual Life.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> I'le aſſure you Sir I came not hithet for the Sermons, but that I hoped by Gods Grace aſſiſting, I ſhould do ſome good.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> What good prethee Son did you think to do here; fith you are a ſimple Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and ignorant of Scriptures, neither per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151173:10"/> to Preach? Pray ſtay here a while, and peradventure by Gods aſſiſtance I will give you ſuch a Sermon, as you will gladly hear.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> There is ſomething Sir that I would willingly have ſpoke to you, but I doubt whether you can patiently bear it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Prethee Son ſpeak boldly what thou haſt to ſay; I truſt in God I ſhall pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently bear it, what ever it be.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Behold Reverend Sir, you gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in your Prieſtly dignity, &amp; lately Preach a Sermon to us full fraught, with excellent precepts; but you take no care to hold them forth in your Life and Converſation, and even now how childiſhly did you ſay to me, ſtay here and I will Preach you another Sermon that ſhall pleaſe me. But take this for certain Sir, that neither your Sermons nor any Words whatever, which can in this Life be outwardly ſpoken, can be much profitable to me. Nay I'le aſſure you, the Sermons of men do oftner do me hurt, then profit me; becauſe that oftentimes various Images (or Imaginations) do inſinuate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into me by reaſon of thoſe Sermons, which afterwards returning home, I can hardly with much and long labour again rid my ſelf of or forget; and (Sir) if you be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151173:10"/> remembred, you had among others, this paſſage in your Sermon. That he ought to be free and clear from all Images (or Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations) to whom the chief Doctor and Teacher of Souls Chriſt Jeſus will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to come; who I will aſſure you as oft as he is pleaſed to come to me, he teacheth me more in the ſpace of an hour, then either you (Maſter Doctor) or all the Doctors in the World, could teach me till Dooms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Prethee, dear Son, for the Lords death ſake, ſtay with me here a longer time.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Truely (Mr. Doctor) you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force me to ſtay by this deep adjuration, and if out of obedience to God, I do yield to ſtay here, it ſhall be upon this condition, that you promiſe me faithfully, that whatever hath paſt or ſhall paſs between us, you will keep ſecret under the privacy of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> That I will aſſure you (dear Son) I will willingly do, upon the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that you will ſtay longer with me. Then the Layman after this manner ſpake to the Doctor.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Mr. Doctor, in your late before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Sermon, you delivered indeed to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151173:11"/> us many excellent good things; yet whilſt you were ſpeaking, ſuch a ſimilitude as this came into my head, that me thought your good diſcourſes did no otherwayes proceed from you, then as if good and generous Wine were drawn through muddy dregs.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Prethee (Son) what meaneſt thou by this ſimilitude.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Nothing elſe (Mr. Doctor) but me thought, your Veſſel was not clean, nor rinced from dreggs; and that's the reaſon that the Letter killeth you, and (alaſs) you dayly ſuffer it, yet dayly more and more to kill you; for (as you better know) the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſaith, the Letter killeth, but the Spirit quickeneth and maketh alive. Nevertheleſs the ſame Letter that now doth kill you, would (if you would) quickly quicken you. But truly at preſent for your condition it is this; You are yet in the Dark, and there is no Light in you, by which you might clearly and diſtinctly underſtand the Letter, and truely as yet you belong to the number of the Phariſees.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> I profeſs (dear Son) ſince the hour I was born, I never heard from any man ſuch hard language.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Very good (Mr. Doctor) I pray where is now your Sermon? See, ſee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151173:11"/> how you are catch'd! but beſides, though it may be my words may ſeem hard to you; yet intruth it is ſo as I have ſaid, as I ſhall eaſily prove even from your ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Really I would willingly ſee that, for I cannot tell that ever I cared for that generation of Phariſees,</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> In the firſt place (Mr. Doctor) give me leave to ſhew you how it is that the Letter killeth you; you know (dear Sir) that as ſoon as ever you came to years of diſcretion, you betook your ſelf to the ſtudy of Books, in which notwithſtanding you did onely ſeek your ſelf, and are not at all even to this day free from that vice; but truely you are (though ſecretly) in your nature, proud, and do much relie upon that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and attribute much to that title of Doctor, wherewith you were honoured; neither have you in all theſe things purely with love and fervency of mind, ſought God onely; Neither out of love have you any Eye to his Glory in all your ſtudies, but do too too much love and ſeek your ſelf in the applauſe and favour of poor Creatures, and that eſpecially in one certain perſon, towards whom you would oft ſteal a look, and whom I fear you do inordinately love. And this is the reaſon why the Letter killeth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151173:12"/> you. That alſo which I ſaid is too too true likewiſe; Namely, that you poſſeſs an empty and an unclean veſſel; For indeed you do not in all your actions purely and ſingly Love God, but in many things you too well know that you ſeek and love your ſelf. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is true that I ſaid, that your Veſſel is empty and foul with Lees; from whence it cometh to paſs, that that good and generous Wine of Heavenly Doctrine, and Divine word, although in its ſelf excellent and pure, yet paſſing through ſuch a Veſſel doth not at all reliſh to a purged mind, that heartily loves and bends towards God; neither doth it profit at all ſuch an one. That which I ſaid beſides; namely, that you did as yet ſit in midnight darkneſs, is alſo moſt true, which will evidently appear from hence, that you cannot ſay that any of the Sermons or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions proceeded from a ſupernatural illumination or Divine Grace, but only from art and ſtudy. Laſtly, in that I did affirm you were a Phariſee, that alſo I prove to be no leſs true, although I will not ſay that you are altogether one of thoſe falſe Phariſees. But tell me (Reverend Sir) did not thoſe falſe Phariſees ſeek and love themſelves, not in all things, purely aiming at the Glory of God! And now pray conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151173:12"/> your ſelf, whether you are not before God a Phariſee, and not a whit better. You do not (I ſuppoſe) doubt, that there are many living this day who in Gods eſteem are no better then Phariſees, yet are ſo more or leſs, according to the condition of their lives and converſations.</p>
               <p>When as the Layman had ſaid theſe things, the Doctor affectually embracing him, kiſſed his Cheek and ſaid; you bring that paſſage into my mind which is not unlike to my caſe, and the ſame things ſeem to have happend unto me, which did to the woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> near the Well; for you have truely laid open and told me, all my moſt hidden, and ſecret miſcarriages; but eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that, that I did ſometimes ſecretly caſt a glance at a certain Perſon, who yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding knows nothing her ſelf, ſith I never yet any way diſcovered to her that I loved her; Neither doth any man living, I am confident, ſuſpect any ſuch thing. And therefore I doubt not but this ſecret was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to you by God; wherefore I do moſt earneſtly entreat you for Chriſts paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſake, that you would be now unto me a Spiritual Father, and accept of me a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſinner for your Son.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Believe it (Reverend Sir) if you
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151173:13"/> perſiſt thus extravagantly to talk, I will ſtay no longer here, but ſpeedily return to my Country.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Nay, but (Son) pray do not ſo, let me entreat you to ſtay a while with me, and I will faithfully promiſe you, that you ſhall have no ſuch Language for the future: And (believe it) I am fully determined to endeavour to amend my Life and take a new courſe, and to that end, do earneſtly deſire the furtherance of your good Counſel, and whatever it be that you ſhall adviſe me, that (by the Grace of God) I will endeavour to follow and effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Truely (Mr. Doctor) that is very neceſſary for you to do, for knowledge of the Letter, hath miſerably puft up and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced very many learned men, ſome of them who were altogether falſe Phariſees, even to the eternal damnation of Hell; but others to a moſt grievous and horrible Purgatory. For (believe it) 'tis no ſmall matter for a Man to receive from God Almighty, ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile a natural underſtanding, and ſo clear a reaſon, as by them to be able to underſtand clearly Divine Scripture; yet ſo to miſpend this pretious talent, as not to ſtudy thereby to ſhape and frame his Life and Converſation, according to the Scripture.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:151173:13"/>
               <head>This enſuing Diſcourſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> contains a Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, what wonderful and ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious things God did work by this <hi>Layman,</hi> and alſo how for this cauſe beſides others, he obtained ſo great Grace and Favour, becauſe God found in him an abſolute reſigned up humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Doct.</label> GOod Son, let me deſire you to take the pains for God ſake, to ſhew me by what means you have attained to ſo perfect a life; how you began, what have been your exerciſes, and finally by what rules you have framed your life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> I'le aſſure you Mr. Doctor, your deſire is altogether a ſimple one; for certainly ſhould I take it upon me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe, or write all thoſe great things, which God Almighty within theſe ſeven years hath vouchſafed to work in me, a miſerable finner, I dare ſay you have not a Book of that Volumn as to be able to contain it all; nevertheleſs, I ſhall willingly tell you ſome things, which at this time are moſt fit for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151173:14"/> you. In the firſt place, it was an exceeding mercy, that God did indulge unto me even this very thing; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amely, that I were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with a true profound and moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned up humility: For my exerciſes it will not much concern you to know what they were, that I obſerved outwardly in my Body, ſith that the diſpoſitions, natures, and complexions, are ſo divers. But this is a ſure rule, that whoſoever doth from the bottom of his heart, humbly reſign up himſelf to God, him God will lead by inward temptations, and outward occurences into ſuch exerciſes, as he knows to be moſt profitable unto him, and ſuch as (if he will) he can beſt bear; for he that is inquiſitive to know from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, what are their exerciſes, is wont for the moſt part to be deceived, and led away. For each man telling his proper exerciſes, when he would fain follow and imitate, no regard being had of his own ſtrength, it's no marvel if he be thereby deceived and lead away. For it oftentimes comes to paſs, that thoſe exerciſes which are very good for one, and exceedingly helpful, may to another, if he perſiſt in the uſing of them, be pernitious and deſtructive. And hence it is, that the Devil very oft is wont with falſe ſuggeſtions to perſwade men, whom he ſees to be of a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151173:14"/> weak nature and conſtitution, to take upon them the moſt ſtrict and rigid excerciſes. To this end, that either thereby they may ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten their dayes, or get an infirm and crazy brain; which thing that you may the better underſtand, I will tell you briefly what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to me at the beginning of my conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. I did peruſe as it happened at that time, a Book which in the German tongue, treats of the Lives of the Saints; and when I marked each of them, their auſteir and ſtrict manner of Life, I began thus to think with my ſelf; theſe were men in this World aſwell as thou, and peradventure did never ſo grievouſly offend God as thou haſt done. Hereupon I had a great mind to imitate each of theſe Saints in ſomething or other, with as ſevere and rigorous excerciſes. Whereby in a little time I contracted ſuch exceeding weakneſs, that I were even at the point of death. But one day above the reſt it happened, that about Sun-riſing, having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond meaſure continued my exerciſe, that through exceeding weakneſs and wearineſs, even whilſt I were at my exerciſe, I fell faſt aſleep: my thought in my ſleep I heard a kind of voyce ſaying to me. Go to, ſelf-will'd man, if you kill your ſelf before your time, you ſhall certainly ſuffer for it moſt grievous
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151173:15"/> puniſhment. But if thou wilt ſuffer thy ſelf to be exerciſed by God, he will do it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely better then thou thy ſelf canſt do, by the counſel of the Devil. At theſe words, eſpecially at the naming of the Devil, ſuch a fear &amp; terrour ſeized one me, that I ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waked out of ſleep, and riſing, began to think with my ſelf, that I had taken up the foreſaid exerciſes raſhly, and without advice; wherefore immediatly I hyed me to a Wood which was cloſe by the place where I then were. There I made my caſe known in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to a certain old Hermite, and entreated him that he would give me his advice. The old man having heard me out, gave me this anſwer: If thou wouldſt have me give thee counſel, you muſt firſt tell me what the manner of your Life hath been, and what have been your exerciſes. I told him as I were bidden, all my ſtrict exerciſes, and how I had read over the Lives of the Saints, and how I had a great mind to imitate them. Then he asked me, by whoſe adviſe did I do thus: I confeſſed to him, that that which I had done, I had done by no mans advice but my own, and out of my own will. If ſo ſaid he, then take it for certain, it was the Devils counſel; and therefore you had need to take great heed that you follow him
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151173:15"/> no more, but reſign and give up your ſelf wholly to God, and he will exerciſe you far better, than either you or the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil can: Therefore according to this old mans advice, I inſtantly gave over my exerciſes, and did with all my heart give up my ſelf wholly to God, and left my ſelf in his hands, to exerciſe me as he thought moſt fit. Truly (Mr. Doctor) I were by nature of an ingenuous temper, and of an excellent complexion, and of a ſubtil wit, even as I perceive you are; onely in this I was ſhort of you, that I had not ſtudied the Scriptures, nor skilled them, which I perceive you do; yet notwithſtanding I was naturally inclined, with ſo ſubtil and ſublime an underſtanding, that as oft as I thought fit to make uſe of it, I found my ſelf capable and apprehenſive of very great and high matters. Hereby once it came to paſs, that by reaſon of the ſubtilty of my underſtanding. I began to think thus with my ſelf; certainly thou art natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally endued with ſo happy a wit &amp; tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing underſtanding, that without all doubt, if thou wouldſt ſeriouſly &amp; intenſly make uſe of it, thou wouldſt be apprehenſive of ſome extraordinary &amp; divine matter, concerning even God himſelf. Which thoughts im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151173:16"/> after their ſuggeſtion, I perceived to be the fallacious Counſel, and peſtilent Advice and Suggeſtion of the Devil: Thereupon I brokeout into theſe words, <hi>O miſchievous and malignant Connſellour, What Advice is this that thou haſt ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted to me?</hi> Verily, if we had ſuch a God as could be apprehended by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I ſhould not value him thus much. After this, one morning when I was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to read morning Prayers, I had an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding vehement deſire, inſomuch that I brake forth in theſe words, and ſaid to the Lord; O moſt merciful God, if it be thy bleſſed Will, make me now by experience to feel ſomething, that may tranſcend and paſs all underſtanding and reaſon. But I had no ſooner ended theſe words, but that a vehement horrour poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed me, becauſe that I ſhould dare to deſire ſo great a favour; and therefore again ſaid unto the Lord, Ah Eternal and ever to be adored Majeſty, pardon I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee this my raſhneſs, for it exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly repents me, to have done this: And how ſhould it be O Lord, that ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable an Earth-worm as I am, and no man, ſhould ever find ſuch a thing to enter into his heart, as to dare to deſire ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151173:16"/> and excelling favour and grace; when as I know ſufficiently, and am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced within my ſelf how vile I am, to how many ſins I am prone, and how that through the whole courſe of my life, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver as I ought, loved my God, or regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him, but have alwayes made my ſelf by reaſon of ſin, ſo odious in the eyes of thy glory, that I know very well, that I am unworthy that the earth ſhould bear me; and therefore ſince I have preſumed to ſuffer ſuch a deſire, of ſo tranſcendent grace to ariſe in me, it is abſolutely need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that my body ſhould undergo direful, and ſuffer bitter things. Having thus ſaid, I ſtrip'd my ſelf, neither did I ceaſe to ſtrike my ſelf with hard ſtripes, till the blood ran about my ſhoulders. And ſo it came to paſs, that whileſt I was revolving ſuch like thoughts in my heart, and ſpake ſuch like words even till Sun-riſing, upon a ſudden an exceeding ſhining light filled my whole Cell, and in that light I fell into an extaſie; ſo that for a time I was deprived both of my Reaſon and Senſes. But Oh! that hour ſeemed extreamly ſhort unto me. And after I came to my ſelf, I found ſo exceeding and ſupernatural im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151173:17"/> preſſion &amp; ſeal of truth upon me, that I had good reaſon to ſay with St. <hi>Peter</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Lord, it is good for us to be here.</hi> For (believe it) in that ſhort hour I did receive more truth, with more clear light, and certain evidence; more truth (I ſay) than what either you, Mr. Doctor, or all the Doctors in the world can teach me, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven till Dooms-day. But (Mr. Doctor) I ſuppoſe I have ſpoken enough already, as much as concerns your preſent ſtate and condition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:151173:17"/>
               <head>This following Diſcourſe, ſhows how the Lord was pleaſed to Convert by the means of this <hi>Layman,</hi> a certain <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan</hi> that lived in a far Country. It ſhews likewiſe how the Holy Ghoſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at this day doth pour forth the ſame Virtue and Grace, upon minds that he finds apt and well prepared to receive it, that he did upon the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> at the day of <hi>Penticoſt:</hi> As alſo it ſheweth, how this <hi>Layman</hi> did at large explain theſe things to the <hi>Doctor;</hi> and how by plain and clear Reaſons he proved the <hi>Doctor</hi> to be a <hi>Phariſee,</hi> and at laſt brought him to this, that he reſolved fully with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to take a new courſe, and amend his life.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ear Son, if thou haſt any thing more to ſay, I would willingly hear it; for truly I have been much taken with thoſe things which you have hitherto diſcourſed of. But above all, I intreat you again that you will ſtay with me, and by no means yet
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151173:18"/> leave me. If you want money to defray your charges, I will willingly ſupply your want, though I do pawn my Books to take up money: only I deſire you by all means to ſtay with me.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Reverend Sir, I pray God reward you for your proffer'd Courteſie toward me. But I would have you know this, that I ſtand not in need either of yours, or any other mans Temporal goods, for God Almighty hath made me his Steward, and I have neer five thouſand Crowns which are Gods, and I would willingly ſpend them all whereſoever it ſhall be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, or where ever God requireth them at my hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> I perceive then, if ſo, that you are Steward of a very rich and munificent Lord: But I cannot ſufficiently admire at what you even now ſpake: That neither I nor all the Doctors in the World, are able to teach you ſo much, even between this and Dooms-day, as you have in one hour lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God. Let me ask you this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Did ſacred Scripture proceed and flow from the Holy Ghoſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Yes, they did without all doubt, and ſo the Catholick Faith teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us to believe. But Mr. Doctor, it
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151173:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> grieveth me that I have ſaid ſo great things unto you, and that you notwithſtanding ſhould talk ſo childiſhly. But ſee you, I will propound one Queſtion to you, and if you can by Scripture or without it reſolve me, I promiſe you I will give you on Gods behalf a thouſand Crowns.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Prethee good Son tell me what Queſtion is that.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> I would know of you (Mr. Doctor) whether you can inſtruct me how I may write a Letter in ſuch a Language, to a certain Pagan living in a far remote Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. that he may be able both to read it, and underſtand it? and how the form and manner of the Letter may be ſuch, that the ſame Pagan by the reading of it, may be converted to the Faith?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Truly (Son) I know not what to ſay to this; for ſuch kind of works as you, are even the works of the Holy Ghoſt. But I beſeech you tell me whether any ſuch thing ever happened unto you, and if you did thereby underſtand by what means this may be done? or whether you your ſelf were not he that did it?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> No Mr. Doctor, it was not I that did it, but the Holy Ghoſt was pleaſed to work ſo by me an unworthy Inſtrument.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151173:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> And truly much may be ſaid touching this matter, but it were too tedious to rehearſe all; for if this whole buſineſs ſhould be written, it would even fill a Volumn. But I ſhall tell you a few paſſages, from whence you may collect the whole matter. There was a certain Pagan, a true hearted honeſt man, and in his way very juſt. This man for a long time together did cry unto Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and daily did call upon him, who crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted both him &amp; all Creatures, and did daily pray after this manner. <hi>O God, thou Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Creator of all things, behold I am born and bred up in this Country, and in the Faith of it. But I perceive the Jews have another Belief, and likewiſe the Chriſtians follow another Faith: do thou therefore O Lord, who art over all, and haſt made all things, ſhew unto me I beſeech thee by</hi> what <hi>ever means it pleaſeth thee, whether there be any other Faith better or truer than this in which I have been born and bred, that I may believe it; and I will willingly and readily obey thee, by taking upon me that Belief. But if thou ſhalt refuſe to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie thus much unto me, and it ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen that I die in this Faith becauſe I know no better, ſurely this will be hard meaſure.</hi> After the Pagan had thus prayed, it came to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151173:19"/> paſs that a Letter was written unto him from me; which when he had read he was converted unto the Chriſtian Faith. He likewiſe did write back again a Letter to me, in which he fully ſhewed how it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened unto him; which Letter I will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you was ſo written in our vulgar High Dutch, as I could very well read it. Many things (Mr. Doctor) remains to be ſpoken concerning this matter, but you have in brief the ſum of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Truly God is wonderful in his gifts, and I will aſſure you (dear Son) theſe are ſtrange and rare matters which you have told me.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Verily I do enough fear (Mr. Doctor) that I have told you more than was fit for me to tell you. And to ſay the truth, I do perceive that I have ſpoken ſomewhat that doth ſomething trouble you, and go againſt your ſtomack. For whereas I am but a Layman, and illiterate, but you a great Dr. of ſacred Divinitie; nevertheleſs I have taken upon me by way of tutoring and teaching, to tell you ſo many things; it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be but this muſt ſomewhat offend you.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Son, if you would not take it ill, I would tell you what doth diſpleaſe me.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:151173:20"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Aſſuredly I will not take it ill, you may ſpeak all your mind freely.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Dear Son, I cannot away with this, but do what I can it goes againſt my ſtomack, that you when as you are a Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſhould teach me a Doctor and a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; as alſo that you ſhould call me a Phariſee.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Is there any thing more in me that doth diſpleaſe you?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Not the leaſt I aſſure you, that I know of.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Will you give me leave pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently (Mr. Doctor) to ſatisfie you in theſe two things.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Dear Son, you have not only free leave, but I again and again deſire you to do it</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Pray tell me (Mr. Doctor) how it ſhould come to paſs, and by whom was it brought about, that the moſt bleſſed Virgin <hi>Katherine,</hi> when ſhe was about four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore years of age, ſhould in diſcourſe and diſpute overcome fifty moſt acute Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, ſo as they did all moſt willingly offer themſelves to die for Chriſt? Tell me I ſay (Mr. Doctor) who was that that did this, or who ſpake there? That one ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Virgin ſhould overcome ſo great Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:151173:20"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> No man doubts but that it was the Holy Ghoſt who did that.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Do you not believe (Mr. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor) that the Holy Ghoſt, is as powerful now as he was then?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Yes I do certainly believe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> And what hinders then, but that you may alſo believe, that the ſame Holy Ghoſt can ſpeak to you by me a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſinner, when as he once deigned to ſpeak by <hi>Caiphas</hi> who alſo was a ſinner. And truly if you ſo hardly bear thoſe things which I have ſpoken, hereafter I ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with you more cautiouſly.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> I entreat you (Son) do no ſo, for I will now correct my ſelf in this matter alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> You ſaid moreover (Sir) that this alſo did ſomwhat gall you, that I ſhould call you a Phariſee: But when I ſaid ſo there was then ſuch an account given of it by me to you, that ought fully to have ſatisfied you. But ſith you were not content with that, I ſhall again with another Reaſon prove to you, that you are more guilty in that point than I then ſaid. Surely you know (Mr. Doctor) that our Saviour doth exhort us in one place, and ſpeaks in this manner; <hi>Beware of the</hi> Phariſees, <hi>for they bind hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151173:21"/> burthens and grievous to be born, and lay them upon mens ſhoulders, but they will not touch them with one of their little fingers.</hi> Now conſider and reflect upon your ſelf a little: Certainly you did lay upon our ſhoulders Twenty four Points, or Articles, which you your ſelf will hardly lightly touch. Likewiſe in another place, our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſpeaks of the ſelf ſame <hi>Phariſees, All whatſoever they ſay unto you, that keep and do, but do not after their works, for they ſay and do not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Thoſe words indeed the Lord ſpake once.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> That's no matter, for he ſpeaks the ſame yet continually. But ſee now (Sir) whether you have not given us moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Rules and Precepts, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding how much you-follow in your Life and Converſation, God knows, and you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo are not ignorant; and as things ſtand with you at preſent, I do willingly follow your Doctrine, but ſhould be very loath to imitate your Life and Converſation: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now I pray judge you your ſelf, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before God you are not truly a Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee; yet not of the number of thoſe falſe and impious Phariſees that deſerve Hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Truly (Son) I have not what
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151173:21"/> to anſwer, but confeſs and acknowledge my ſelf to be a ſinner. And now I deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine to amend my life, though I ſhould hereby incur the hazard of death. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can I any longer defer it, but do again and again entreat and beſeech you (Son) that purely for Gods ſake you would Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel me, how I may begin a better life, and that you would alſo ſhew me by what means I may attain the higheſt perfection, which in this life may be attained.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> It is very hard (good Sir) let it be ſpoken under favour, to give you any Counſel in this matter; for your life and manner of converſation which you have hetherto led, and been uſed to, you have by long cuſtom turned almoſt into another nature. So that if you ſhould deny and ceaſe from your long accuſtomed manner and courſe of life, (which of neceſſity you muſt do) it could not be, without grievous trouble and anguiſh to your nature; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſith you are (if I miſtake not) about 50 years of age.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Thereabout indeed (dear Son) I think is my age; But what then? they that came at the eleventh hour had their full wages, and received their penny. And therefore now I am fully reſolved and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151173:22"/> in mind (though I were certain there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſuffer death) from hence forward to turn over a new leaf, to change my courſe, and to renounce, deny and forſake my old fallacious life (that was onely given to ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation and curioſities of wit) and alſo to deny all vice, and all manner of ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; and endeavour by the grace of God, to order my life for the future after your Advice and Counſel. Wherefore I moſt earneſtly entreat, that laying aſide all delay, you would inſtruct and teach me for Gods ſake, how I may begin the reformation and amendment of my life; for I cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it ſhould any longer be deferred or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Well (honoured Sir) ſith there is ſuch grace conferred upon you by God, that you refuſe not to humble your ſelf, but are willing to ſubmit your ſelf to a vile poor creature. It concerns us in the firſt place to give God the honour, due to him. And ſith it muſt be, that I for Gods ſake am to give Counſel and Advice to you, I ſhall humbly ſeek Gods help; and that I may be the better able, I ſhall do it from his. love, and for the love of him. In the firſt place, truly I ſhall begin to teach you after the ſame manner as they inſtruct
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151173:22"/> Children at School; that is, I ſhall commend to you a certain ſpiritual Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, conſiſting of 23 Articles or Sentences, ſo many as there are letters in the Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, with which they begin to teach Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="alphabet">
                  <body>
                     <head>Here followeth a Golden Alphabet, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the <hi>Layman</hi> to the <hi>Doctor,</hi> that by it he might begin to mend his life. Frequently to read which, and according to lead our lives, without doubt would be exceeding profitable to us All.</head>
                     <list>
                        <head>A Golden Alphabet.</head>
                        <item>
                           <label>A</label> ATtempt in the fiſt place, and ſet upon a good, pure, and ſpiritual life, not triflingly or childiſhly, but ſtoutly, and with a reſolved manly mind.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>B</label> Both do good, and ſhun evil, and that carefully and diligently.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>C</label> Conſerve, and keep the moſt congruous and modeſt mean in all things.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>D</label> Diligently learn to bear about with you, both inwardly and outwardly, modeſty and humility.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>E</label> Extirpate and utterly deny for Gods ſake your own will, that ſo you may remain in union with God.</item>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:151173:23"/>
                        <item>
                           <label>F</label> Fervently, conſtantly, and ſeriouſly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in God.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>G</label> Give your ſelf with joy, ſimply and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly to obey, and ſhew thy ſelf willing and ready without murmuring to all, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is of God.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>H</label> Hanker not after, nor look back upon the world.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>I</label> Inwardly accuſtom thy ſelf to ruminate and meditate in thy heart, upon divine and ſpiritual matters, and with tears bewail and deplore thy former life.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>K</label> Keep conſtant guard, and couragiouſly reſiſt the temptations of the Devil, the World, and the Fleſh.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>L</label> Leaving behind all temporal things, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with a cheerful and valiant mind after Eternal.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>M</label> Mind alwayes to preſerve a love to God, and your Neighbour.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>N</label> Never covet any mans goods, of what nature ſoever they be.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>O</label> Orderly make the beſt of all things, and never turn any thing to the worſt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>P</label> Puniſhment, and remorſe for ſin, from whence ſoever it happen to you, whether from God or from Creatures, take it kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and receive it with a ſubmiſſive mind.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Q</label> Quietly and heartily forgive all, what
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151173:23"/> ever they be, that have offended you, or done you any injury, in thought, word or deed.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>R</label> Retain with all poſſible diligence, thy chaſtity, both of Body and Soul.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>S</label> Seriouſly obſerve meekneſs and mildneſs in all things, and ſtudy to be made better by all things.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>T</label> Take heed that without guile, hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie or fraud, you keep your Word, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Faith with all men; and exerciſe your ſelf in works of charity, both bodily and ſpiritual, according to your ability.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>V</label> Vigilantly take heed, neither in eating or in drinking, or any other matter you exceed due meaſure.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>X</label> XTS. Life and Doctrine revolve always in your mind, and to the utmoſt of your power imitate it, and lead your life accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Y</label> Ymportune the undefiled Virgin-mother with devout Prayers, that ſhe may be aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting to you in the through learning this my Inſtitution.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Z</label> Zealouſly accuſtom your ſelf with ſevere Diſcipline, to keep under and bridle your will, and ſenſual affections; that they mildly yield to what ever God ſhall do with you, or ſuffer to happen to you.</item>
                     </list>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:151173:24"/>
               <head>How the <hi>Doctor</hi> ſoon, though not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out labour, truly learn'd the Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betical Inſtitution: How after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the <hi>Layman</hi> taught him a nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer way to perfection. Moreover, how the <hi>Doctor</hi> was fain to enter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a dying Life; and therein ſo long exerciſed himſelf, until he had overcome himſelf.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> GO to now (Mr. Doctor) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this childiſh Inſtitution from God, who delivereth the ſame unto you by me an unworthy ſinner.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> To you peradventure (dear Son) this Inſtitution ſeems but childiſh; but I confeſs to you, me thinks, it is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man-like: but be it what it will be, I am reſolved by the grace of God to take upon me the learning of it. But pray tell me, what time will you ſet me to learn it in.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> For the honour of Chriſts five wounds, which are the ſigns of his immea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable love to us, take five weeks, that ſo you may the more perfectly learn it. In which time you muſt be your own School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151173:24"/>
                  <note place="margin">1. Whip your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſhoulders with Rods.</note> and enjoyn your ſelf ſharp pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, if you miſtake and happen to fail in any of theſe Articles, or to do any thing contrary to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> I'le follow your Counſel (Son) and undergo all your Injunctions.</p>
               <p>Now when 3 weeks were near ſpent in this manner of living, the Layman enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Doctor, how it was with him. To whom the Doctor anſwered, I will aſſure you dear Son, I have in theſe three weeks undergone more and ſharper pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in the learning of this your Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than in all the ſtudies of my whole life paſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> But how is it with you now (Mr. Doctor) are you skilful in the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and Letters of the Alphabet as yet?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> How much ſoever I be Maſter of it (and by the grace of God, things go well enough with me) yet I would willingly more perfectly skill it. But moreover, I beſeech you inſtruct me further, and ſhew me yet more perfect things.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> You very well know Sir, that in Schools they never ſet boyes higher Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, till they have well learned their firſt Elements.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> I confeſs, then (dear Son) I
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151173:25"/> ſhould be guilty of a lye, if I ſhould ſay, I have throughly learned your Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Therefore it is more adviſed for us to proceed no further, till you have perfectly learned it.</p>
               <p>Afterward, when again about 3 weeks more were ſpent, the Doctor ſent a friend to the Layman, to deſire him to ſtep to him, who accordingly preſently came; and the Doctor ſaid to him, <hi>O Son rejoice with me, for I ſuppoſe now through the grace of God, I am pretty perfect in the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet;</hi> and if you pleaſe, I will willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give you an account of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> There is no need Sir, that you ſhould ſo do; for I doubt not of the truth of what you ſay; and do much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate you.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Maſter.</label> Truly Son, with much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty have I learned this Inſtitution; but now I beſeech you farther to inſtruct me.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Take it for certa in Mr. Doctor, that of my ſelf I cannot farther inſtruct you, but if it pleaſe Almighty God farther by me to inſtruct you, I hope I ſhall not be backward to do my beſt endeavour, and will be a willing, although an unworthy inſtrument of his, by whom he may do
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151173:25"/> what he pleaſe; neither ſhall I in the leaſt advice you to any thing, but what he ſhall give in, and ſupply me with, &amp; this I will do ſingly, &amp; of the pure love of God, &amp; deſire of your Salvation. And if it ſhall happen unto you, as it did to the young man in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, who when he heard the Counſel of our Lord, to ſell and leave all that he had, went away ſorrowful; if (I ſay) it ſhall ſo fall out with you, I for my part will be ſolely blameleſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Let not that (Son) at all trouble you, for I am fully reſolved in my mind, not to regard at all what can in this matter befall me; but purpoſe to follow and obey Gods and your Counſel.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Well (Sir) ſith you now are of ſo reſolved and ready a mind: I do in the firſt place out of charity and the love of God adviſe you, that by all means you remain obedient to your Order, and to all your Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours; For it cannot be but that if you enter upon the right, ſtraight and narrow way, you will be grievouſly oppreſled and vexed; and that chiefly by your Order and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. And when this ſhall befall you, ſtraight-ways your ſubtile underſtanding, and ſenſual nature, will be deviſing many things, and urging you to go to the chief Biſhop,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151173:26"/> or ſome whither, and find a thouſand ways whereby to avoid this Croſs. But herein you muſt take great heed, and rather bear patiently what ever ſhall happen grievous unto you, and continually perſevere in hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obedience; for truly the ſame way that our Lord ſhewed unto the fore-named young man, that way muſt you go, you muſt take up your Croſs upon your ſhoulders, and follow the Lord and Saviour, and in ſome meaſure his example, and that with true, great, and patient humility: Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more you muſt renounce and deny that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, ſubtile and pompous underſtanding, which you have acquired out of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. And for a while give over all read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſtudying and preaching. And when thoſe that uſed to make their confeſſions to you, ſhall come again unto you to that end, you muſt ſhew your ſelf in ſimplicity; and confeſſion being made, immediatly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from them, ſpeaking nothing, nor gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them any counſel, but only ſaying, I will firſt learn how I may counſel my ſelf, and when I have well learned ſo to do, I will be ready to inpart advice to you. And if they be inquiſitive when you will preach, you may without injury to the truth, ſimply and nakedly anſwer, that at the preſent you
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151173:26"/> are wholly taken up with another buſineſs. So by this means you will by little and little, alienate and eſtrange your ſelf from men.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> If preaching be forbid me, there is nothing then (Son) that I have to employ my ſelf in: what therefore ſhall I do?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Betake your ſelf to your Cell, and there perform your hourly Prayers, and as oft as you can, do the ſame, in Quire with others. Likewiſe every day, except ſome juſt occaſion hinder you perform Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſervice, and celebrate the Maſs. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, what ever time remains, you ſhall ſpend it in meditating of the Life, Death, and Paſſion, and example of Chriſt; diligently conſidering how unlike your Life is to His. <note place="margin">Iſa. 32.</note> Here call to mind, and in the bitterneſs of your Soul, think of the years, and all the time paſt, in which you have ſinfully loved your ſelf, taking notice how little your love hath been to God: and contrary-wiſe, how great his love hath been to you. Of theſe things Sir, let your ſtudy humbly be, for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it may ſo come to paſs, that by degrees you may attain to true humility, and change your old converſation, and antient Cuſtome into a better. Furthermore, when that time ſhall come, which God well knows; he will on a ſudden change you into a new, and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151173:27"/> another man. But before this regeneration can be wrought in you, you muſt firſt ſell all whatever you poſſeſs, and humbly reſign all unto God; Namely, you ought wholly to renounce and deny, all your curioſity and ſubtility of your ſences, and underſtanding; and whatever it be, by which you may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire honour or delight to your ſelf; and laſtly, all that delight, which hitherto you have poſſeſt in your nature, and in which according to your nature, you have falſly, and inordinately found reſt; <note place="margin">Luk. 7.10</note> and with bleſſed <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> humbly caſt your ſelf pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate at the Feet of your Lord. For indeed you muſt totally dye to all theſe things fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned. Now if you ſhall begin to ſet upon theſe things, you will render your ſelf a pleaſant, and acceptable ſpectacle to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God: who indeed cannot behold theſe things without delight: and it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, he will not leave, but will drive and compel you to ſuch tryals as were of old, that you may ſo much the more be proved, and be throughly purified as gold in a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace; It may be (I ſay) he will reach out to you in ſome meaſure that cup of love, which he gave to his only begotten Son: which is, that it may ſo fall out, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you do or leave undone, yea, and your
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151173:27"/> whole courſe of life may be diſeſteemed, and deſpiſed of all: and thoſe, who have hitherto been wont to confeſs themſelves to you, may ſtand a far off from you, as one deſtitute of ſenſe and reaſon: yes, and all your friends, and a great part of your Brethren, that live with you in your Monaſtery, may be offended and ſcandalized at your life, and may ſay one to the other, that you have taken up a ſtrange and unuſual way of life, ſuch as hath almoſt rendred you a dolt, or fool. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when as theſe things ſhall happen unto you, ſee Sir that by no means you be terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, but rather triumph in your God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your Salvation is nigh. Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your frail nature (without doubt) will be ſomething terrified at this; but do you ſtoutly truſt in God, who will by no means forſake you. Furthermore, when you ſhall be brought into this diſtreſs, it can hardly be, but that at ſometime or other, it will come into your mind, to ask and deſire of God, that he would vouchſafe unto you ſome ſupernatural conſolation, and make you to taſte ſome ſweetneſs; which when it ſhall happen to you, be ſure ſuch a deſire is not from God; but from hence rather, that as yet, there is ſome pride lurking in your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For truly, it is great preſumption for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151173:28"/> any to be ſo bold, as to ask of God ſuch ſupernatural Gifts. And therefore if this ſhould befall you, that you ſhould perceive any ſuch deſire to ariſe in you; inſtantly ſet your ſelf againſt it with your whole ſtrength, and ſupreſs it with very great and humble reſignation, ſaying both with heart and voice; <hi>Ah moſt Merciful God, it doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly, and from the bottom of my heart grieve and diſpleaſe me, and I very much lament, becauſe I perceive ſo great and high a deſire to ariſe in me; when as I clearly perceive I am altogether unworthy of ſuch great gifts; yea, and unworthy that the Earth ſhould bear me.</hi> And when you ſhall utter theſe words with your mouth, although as yet you be not ſo perfectly ſenſible in your heart; be not much terrified: but only as oft as ſuch like deſires ſhall ariſe in you, you muſt puniſh your ſelf with Rods. But if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſuch means, ſuch thoughts will ceaſe, then endure them as a temptation, ſo long as God pleaſeth, you ſhould bear them. Finally (worthy Sir) if you reſolve to undergo this courſe of life; you will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive nothing more profitable to you, then that with a profound and couragious reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you humbly commit your ſelf to God in all things, which ſhall happen to you,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151173:28"/> whether they be ſweet, or whether they be bitter, whether they delight, or whether they torment; ſo as that you may be able truly to ſay unto God; <hi>O moſt Merciful God, and moſt worthy to be adored, although it were thy Will, that I ſhould remain in this life, and in this heavy preſſure even till the laſt day of Judgment; yet I would by no means forſake thee, but conſtantly and ever adhere, and cleave to thee.</hi> Verily Sir, I ſufficiently in the Grace of God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that this thought now is in your heart, that you may juſtly inwardly ſay to your ſelf, that what ever hath hitherto been ſpoken by me, is extream hard and difficult. And therefore I before made this proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, If it ſhall happen that you ſtart aſide from what is propoſed to you, (as did that Young man fore-mentioned) then I will be free from all blame.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Maſter.</label> It is (dear Son) very true, which you ſay; and moreover this your laſt ſpeech ſeems to me yet more hard.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> And yet Sir, you intreated me, to ſhew you the neareſt way to the higheſt perfection attainable in this life. And truly, I know no way more ſecure, then that, which leads to the imitation of the example of the moſt Holy Humanity of Chriſt.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151173:29"/> Wherefore I ſincerely advice you, to take ſufficient time of conſideration, and betake your ſelf into your ſelf; and whatever by Divine inſpiration you ſhall underſtand, ought to be done by you, that, you may ſafely ſet upon.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Maſter.</label> I like well (Son) your counſel, and intend to follow it: and as I ſhall be able, I will take heed by the aſſiſtance of Divine Grace to overcome my ſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>What afterwards befel the <hi>Doctor.</hi> How he endured grievous preſſures in his nature, and underwent the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of men, inſomuch that his ſtrength began to fail him.</head>
               <p>ABout eight dayes after, the Doctor ſent a certain Meſſenger to the Layick, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him to come to him; And when he was come, the Maſter ſaid to him: Ah moſt dear ſon, it can hardly be uttered, what fightings, what grief, what ſtrife, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, I have inwardly undergone both night and day, before with Gods aſſiſtance, I could ſo far attain, as that I might over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Devil, the Fleſh, and my own Nature. But now through the Grace of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151173:29"/> God I have obtained an undanted, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy mind, and alſo a true and perfect will; ſo that I will chearfully (God aſſiſting) enter upon that way, which you have taught me: and although (likely) it will be very trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome to my Nature, yet that ought pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently to be endured, neither ſhall I for that cauſe draw back, but will through the Grace of God perſevere ſteady and conſtant in this purpoſed courſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Do you keep ſtill in your memory (Doctor) thoſe Words which I lately ſpake to you?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Maſter.</label> Immediately after you left me, I carefully wrote them all down.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> I congratulate to you Sir, &amp; hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejoyce with you, that you have obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo ready, ſo vigorous, and ſo undanted a mind; neither do I in this leſs wiſh well to you, than I do to my ſelf. Therefore now ſafely in the Name of God begin, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have your ſelf manlike. And ſo taking his leave, the Layick departed.</p>
               <p>Now the Doctor obeying the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and counſel of the Layick, preſently ſet upon the work: And forthwith forbore every thing, that he was required to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear. In ſo much, that before a year was come about, he was as much had in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151173:30"/> by all, that lived with him in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery, as he was before had in eſteem, and honour; yea, and his ſpecial friends, and as many (whether men or women) as were wont to confeſs themſelves to him; finally, all that knew him, and reſpected him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo eſtranged from him, as if they had never ſeen him: which was not a little trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome and contrary to his nature. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, he began to feel much infirmity and weakneſs in his head, which ſtruck him with greater terrour, than all the reſt. Wherefore by a Meſſenger he ſent for the Layman, and declared to him, all that had befallen him, and how that his natural ſtrength began to fail: but chiefly how he was not a little diſtreſſed, by reaſon of the infirmity of his head. The Layman made him this anſwer. Be not terrified Sir, but humbly reſign your ſelf to God, and put your truſt firmly in him. Truely, I hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto well am pleaſed, and like matters, as they ſtand with you; and indeed things are very well with you, and will be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter without doubt; you well know; that he that will find the right Way, and walk therein, muſt through ſome ſufferings at leaſt, and afflictions, follow the example of Truth it ſelf; namely, our Saviour Chriſt.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151173:30"/> Therefore in the leaſt be not terrified at all, but leave your ſelf totally to God; for it thus heretofore befel me likewiſe. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding in the mean time, whileſt this infirmity is upon you, you may diſcretly ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour your Nature, by the uſe of better meat. I had made for me, when I were in the like infirmity, a certain confection of Aromatical druggs, which did comfort my head; and the like I'le get made for you. But this is certain, that I alwayes left my ſelf totally to God, to do with my Soul or Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy what he pleaſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Maſter.</label> But now you teach me other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, &amp; adviſe me to relieve &amp; ſuccour my ſelf with better meat, in this my infirmity.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> No man ought Sir to tempt God; ſo long as you continue in this weakneſs, God doth freely permit you to help and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort your nature, &amp; eſpecially your head. Go to now Sir, &amp; with Divine aſſiſtance go on as you have begun, joyfully reſign up your ſelf to God in all things, with true &amp; deep humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Put your truſt in God, and wait for his grace, and whatever he then requires of you, whether it be ſweet, or whether it be bitter, be ſure to the utmoſt of your ſtrength to yield him obedience. As for my part, I pray you for Gods ſake, take it not ill,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151173:31"/> that I can no longer at this time abide with you. For a weighty buſineſs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels me at this time to bid you fare-well. But if you cannot ſpare me altogether, ſend ſome body to that place, and there I'le be found. But it would be far better for you, if you could go on without the comfort of any mortal creature.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Maſter.</label> Do not (I beſeech you dear Son) ſay ſo; for indeed I cannot long want you. And truly it afflicts me much, and fills my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ind with vehement anguiſh, becauſe you now will depart from me. But ſith, as you ſay, ſo weighty a buſineſs, and which concerns God, compels you to be gone; I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and reſign my ſelf, and bear your ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence as well as I may.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Now therefore Sir, ſith you are brought under the Rod, and ſcourge of the Lord, to which alſo you have offered your ſelf willingly, it concerns you very much to lead your life diſcretly. Be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful therefore to give your ſelf your juſt due. And let it not diſturb you, that you are forſaken by Creatures. But if you ſhould want money, pawn ſome of your Books, and borrow upon them; but take heed that you ſell not one of them. For if I be not miſtaken, the time will come, when they
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151173:31"/> will be all neceſſary to you. Having thus ſaid, the Layman bidding the Doctor fare-well, departed; the Doctor in the mean time weeping for his departure, and commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How the <hi>Doctor</hi> was wonderfully viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, touched, and illuminated by God: and how the <hi>Layman</hi> returned to him again, and meekly exerted him, that he ſhould again take upon him the care of Preaching, which for ſome time had been omitted.</head>
               <p>VVHen as now the Doctor had for 2. years together continued in moſt grievous temptations, together with the great contempt of all his Friends and extream poverty, inſomuch that he was compelled to borrow money, upon ſome of his Books, which he pawned; and alſo had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone with much humility the grievous weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his whole nature: It came to paſs that night, which immediately goes before the day celebrated for the Converſion of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that a moſt grievous Temptation ruſhed upon him, ſuch as the heart of man cannot
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151173:32"/> imagine, whereby he conceived ſuch a great weakneſs of his whole nature, that that night he was not able to go forth to Morning-Prayer, but abode ſitting in his Cell, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning himſelf from the bottom of his heart to God, with huge and true humility, being deſtitute of all help and comfort from any mortal Creature whatever. And whileſt he was kept in this weakneſs, he began a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other things to meditate on the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, thinking with himſelf, with what infinite love Jeſus Chriſt did follow him; and contrariwiſe, he reflecting upon his own life, perceiving how unconſiderable his life was, if compared with the Life of Chriſt, and how as nothing his life was, compared with the immence charity of Chriſt. Great contrition, and ſorrow for all his ſins, and for all his ill ſpent and loſt time, ceazed upon him. So that with his whole affection, with heart and voice he ſaid to the Lord: <hi>Ah! mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful and compaſſionate Lord God, have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, have mercy upon me for the abiſs of thy mercies ſake, becauſe I am not worthy that the earth ſhould bear me.</hi> Whileſt theſe words were in his heart and mouth, being broad awake, he heard with his bodily cars (yet ſeeing nothing) a voice ſaying
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151173:32"/> unto him. <hi>Now receive thy peace, and put thy truſt in God; and take it for certain, that when he lived upon earth, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſick perſon he cured in body, the ſame he likewiſe healed in Soul.</hi> Which words being ended, inſtantly the Doctor fell into an extaſie, and was deprived of all rational underſtanding, inſomuch that he knew not what was done unto him, where he was, or whither he was ſnatch'd. But after that he was reſtored to himſelf, he found in himſelf in his whole nature, a new and great power, and vigour; ſuch as he confeſſed he had never in all his whole life time felt by experience before; as alſo ſo clear and enlightned a diſcerning, or illuminated rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as never was in the leaſt known to him before that time. But being amazed, he wondred with himſelf, from whence theſe things ſhould ſo ſuddenly happen unto him, and began to think thus with himſelf. Certainly thou wilt never be able to clear up this matter of thy ſelf, ſend therefore for thy Friend to come unto thee, and lay open the whole matter in order unto him. And ſo he did. The Layman being ſent for, readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obeyed the Doctor, came to him forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; the Doctor told him every thing in order, as it happened unto him; which
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151173:33"/> when the Layman had beard, he ſaid. How gladly, even with my whole heart Sir, do I hear this news. I know that you have firſt now truly experienced the true grace of God, and are now firſt touched in the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior powers of your mind. Know alſo, that as heretofore the Letter killed you, ſo now the ſame will quicken you, becauſe all the holy Scripture proceeded and flowed from the holy Ghoſt. Neither doubt Sir, but the knowledge of the holy Scripture will for the future very much profit you now that you have been found worthy to be illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by the light of the holy Ghoſt. For many things now will be made manifeſt to you by the Scriptures, which were altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unknown to you before. For you know, that the holy Scripture ſeemed to you, and many other Theologiſts, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it ſelf in many places. But he who rightly knows how to look into it, in the light of the holy Spirit (as you hence-for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward will be able to do) ſuch a one doth plainly know, how that it agreeth with it ſelf throughout. Wherefore now you will begin wiſely to underſtand Scripture, and rightly to follow the true Pattern and Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler of Truth, our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo you muſt again take upon you the care of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151173:33"/> Preaching, which for ſome time hath been intermitted; that by the Word you may edifie and inſtruct your Neighbours. And now the time is come alſo, that you muſt fetch home your Books again, and fall to reading, and peruſing them. And be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that hereafter, one Sermon of yours will be more profitable and fruitful, than a hundred of your former; for thoſe that ſhall hear you hereafter, will be profited and amended far more, than they have been heretofore; and that, becauſe the Word which you ſhall hereafter utter, will flow from a clean veſſel, and therefore will be very grateful and acceptable to a clean mind, and a lover of God. Furthermore, know this that as heretofore you have been by many accounted contemptible, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to them diſpicable; ſo now you will appear to them all, an hundred times more amiable, and be more acceptable than ever heretofore. And now multitudes of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will begin to flock together to hear you; ſo that it will for this cauſe be exceeding good for you, to keep your ſelf very humble, and more carefully to watch over your ſelf. For as you know, he that hath any great Treaſure, hath the more need carefully to guard them from Robbers. And certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151173:34"/> thoſe helliſh Robbers, the evil ſpirits are very much affrighted and always terrified, as often as they perceive that God Almighty hath beſtow'd upon any man ſo great a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And therefore be ſure, they will turn every ſtone, and make uſe of all their ſtrength and cunning, to ſteal from you, or rob you of this Treaſure. Therefore it exceedingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you to keep it with all care and vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancy. But you will be able, by no means better to preſerve it, then by a ſilent, true and profound humility. Finally, as things are with you, there is no more need that for the future, I ſhould converſe with you, as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructer of you; No verily, I now exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire to be taught by you, and intend here to remain ſo long, till I have heard di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of your Sermons. And becauſe (as you have acknowledged) you have felt and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced a certain great power, and ſuch as is underſtood both in Nature and Grace; I very much deſire, if the Lord permit that you would again Preach.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Maſter.</label> What advice therefore do you give me, (deareſt Son) for I have pawned ſeveral of my Books, and have taken up upon them, no leſs then thirty Crowns.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Send ſome body for them, and I on (Gods behalf) will redeem them, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151173:34"/> will give thee ſo many Crowns; and if after you have redeemed your Books, any thing ſhall remain, you ſhall reſtore it to God: ſo the Books were brought and redeemed.</p>
               <p>After theſe things, the Doctor cauſed it to be given out, and ſpread abroad, that upon the third day after he intended to Preach; which when it was heard, every body much wondered; and becauſe of the novelty of the thing, a huge multitude of People came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. The Doctor therefore when he was come, and ſaw ſo many People come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, got up into the Pulpit, and covering his Eyes with his hood, he thus prayed to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>O Mercyful God, of it may be pleaſing to thee, grant I may ſo ſpeak and do, as that thy moſt acceptable will may be done in me.</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after he had ſpoken theſe Words. 2 pang of weeping without any endeavour of his, fell upon him, &amp; he ſhed many moſt ſweet Tears; which continued ſo long, that the People began to be weary of ſo tedious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, So that one of the crowd; ſaid with a loud voyce; How long (I pray Sir) do you intend to keep us? Now it grows late, and if you will not begin, ſay ſo, that we may riſe and go home. And when the Doctor himſelf did take notice, that the time was nigh paſt; he ſaid again unto the Lord.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151173:35"/> 
                  <hi>Ah Merciful Lord my God, if it be thy will ſtop theſe Tears, and grant I may Preach this Sermon! Which thing if thou deny me, I fear that thou judgeſt, I have not yet been ſufficiently derided, notwithſtanding fullfil in me all thy good pleaſure according to thy will.</hi> But whatever he ſaid, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he pray'd, he nothing at all availed: but his Tears rather more prevailed. Perceiving therefore that it was the Divine will &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; he ſaid to the People weeping. Truly beloved, it ſufficiently grieves me that you have been ſo long in expectation. But ſo it is, that I cannot at this time bring forth one Word. When the People heard this, they aroſe and went their way. And ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the fame of this paſſage ſpread it ſelf through the whole City; So that then again, the Doctor began to be laugh'd at, and to be had in contempt; every one ſaying; See now we perceive as clear as none-day, that he is ſtark mad, and deprived of his Reaſon and Sences. Whereupon his Brethren did ſeverely and ſolemnly ſuſpend him from his Office of Preaching, telling him that he brought upon them no ſmall damage and ſhame, ſince by his ſingular and unuſual manner of living, he had weakened his brain. Among theſe troubles, the Doctor ſent for
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151173:35"/> the Layman, and told him in order all that had befaln him The Layman anſwered him; Be of good courage (worthy Sir) neither let any terror take hold of you: it is certain your affairs were never in ſo good plight as now they are; for the Omnipotent God will have you wholly to be his friend. And therefore it is probable, that till then ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of pride lay hid in your mind, which now God hath mortified in you; when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet up in a high place, after the Example of Chriſt, you were derided by men. And truly you ought with a willing mind to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſo great a Gift of God; for be confident, what remainder of ſin lay hid in you, is now wholly aboliſhed and caſt out. Wherefore Sir, be of good courage, and humbly bear with patience this your humiliation. Neither let this ſeem to you a new and unuſual mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for I have alſo known the like befal others. And take heed that you do in no wiſe condemn this burden of the Croſs, which the Lord hath ſent you. But be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by me, to retire your ſelf from all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane converſe, for this five days, in honour of the five Wounds of Chriſt. Afterwards you may ſpeak with your Pryor, and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture he will permit you to Preach in ſome Monaſtry. But if he ſhall deny you, entreat
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151173:36"/> him that he would firſt make tryal of you, and give you leave once in your Covent, to read a Lecture to your Brethren. To all which words of the Layman, the Doctor yielded obedience willingly; five days being ſpent, and leave being asked and obtained of the Pryor; The Doctor read ſo excellent a Lecture to his Brethren, that they did all exceedingly admire his excellent, Spiritual and Divine Doctrine. So that preſently it was concluded by them all in the Chapter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, that they would make tryal of him once more, granting him leave once more to Preach to the People. Wherefore they gave order to one of the Brothers, who was to Preach in a certain Covent, that after Sermon he give notice to the People, that the Doctor intended the next day to Preach in that place. Therefore that Brother, after he had ended his Sermon, ſaid to the People, I am commanded to give you notice, that to morrow in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none in this Place, the Doctor intends to Preach. But if any thing befal him like that which lately happened to him, impute it in no wiſe to me, ſeeing I do but what I am commanded. Yet take this for certain, that lately he read to us in our Covent, ſuch a Lecture, ſo Excellent, ſo Divine, Profound
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151173:36"/> and Spiritual, that many of our fraternity dare ſay, they have not theſe many years heard ſo Divine and Heavenly Doctrine. But what he will do before you I know not. The next day after the Doctor went to the Monaſtry appointed (it was a Monaſtry of Virgins;) And when he was thither come, he began his Sermon as followeth.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="sermon">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Rare and Devout Sermon, which the <hi>Doctor</hi> Preached in a certain Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery after his Illumination, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt the true Bridegroom of the Soul: and how the Soul ought to follow him in True, Modeſt, Humble and Patient Reſignation: and how Chriſt doth firſt divers wayes prove the Soul, and at laſt gratiouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth it. This Sermon may not unfitly be Preached upon the Feſtival of ſome Virgine.</head>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>
                           <p>Behold the Bridegroom cometh, go you forth to meet him, <bibl>
                                 <hi>Ma.</hi> 25.</bibl>
                           </p>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>IT is now two years ago (if I be not deceived Dearly Beloved) ſince I laſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151173:37"/> Preached unto you; and in that my laſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, I delivered to you 24 Particulars, or Articles. And as you may remember, it was my uſual cuſtom at that time to mingle many Latine Words and Sentences in my Sermons, which for the future I ſhall in no wiſe do. But when I have a mind to uſe the Latine tongue, I will do it amongſt thoſe who are skilful in that Language, and can underſtand what I have to ſay. But now for the obtaining of Divine grace and aſſiſtance, let us ſay over the Angels Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
                     <p>The Verſe which I have pitched upon for my Text (Dearly Beloved) and to which I ſhall confine my ſelf throughout my whole diſcourſe, is this: <hi>Behold the Bridegroom cometh, go you forth to meet him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Bridegroom, is Chriſt Jeſus; the the Spouſe, is humane nature. We there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all (Dearly Beloved) are called Spou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Chriſt, and we ought therefore in duty to go forth to meet him. But alas! the fault is on our part. For the true Wayes and right Pathes, which lead to meet the Bridegroom, are become very deſart and overgrown: And we, alas! do little take notice of them, and too ſeldom and very
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151173:37"/> rarely now adayes is any one found, that entred into thoſe Pathes. But there are many other Roads, in which multitudes go aſtray. So that rarely do any now ariſe and go forth to meet the Bridegroom, as I ſhall God willing hereafter ſhew you. But now, leaſt I ſhould be too tedious, I will in ſilence paſs over. But whereas we are all called Spouſes, I muſt firſt lay open what behoveth every Spouſe to do, that ſhe may go forth to meet her Bridegroom. Firſt therefore, it is the duty of every faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Spouſe, to be baſhful and modeſt, and to avoid all things that may offend her Bridegroom; as for example, ſuch as the vain glory of this fallacious and ill-reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing world, pride, envy, and other common ſins of the world: Alſo, all the pleaſures of corrupt nature, whether it be in profit or idleneſs, or in any other things whatever, but what are upon a true and rational ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count neceſſary. And when the Spouſe hath rejected ſuch and the like things for the love of her Bridegroom, then ſhe beginneth ſomewhat to pleaſe her Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom. Secondly, If thou wilt yet more pleaſe him, ſhe muſt humbly bow and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline her ſelf, and offer up her whole ſelf
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151173:38"/> unto him, ſaying both with heart and voice, <hi>Ah moſt ſweet Lord and Bridegroom, thou knoweſt the hearts of all; therefore I do with my whole heart profeſs unto thee, that I will freely and with a willing mind do all whatever I ſhall know or be able, which thou teaching me, I ſhall ſee to be acceptable and pleaſing to thee, neither will I ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from thee, but perpetually and with all my might cleave unto thee.</hi> When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Spouſe hath thus bethrothed her ſelf, the Bridegroom now turning his face, to her begins to behold her, and commands that ſome rich Jewel be given her; you will ask me what Jewel? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, ſuch an one as this, namely, That ſhe be ſuſſered to be exerciſed both inwardly &amp; outwardly with divers temptations, as his manner is to do with all his ſingular and choice Friends. Then it falls out, that if the Spouſe be yet ſomewhat tender and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate, ſhe ſtrait addreſſes her ſelf to her Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, ſaying. <hi>Ah my moſt merciful Lord, theſe are exceeding ſtrange and unuſual things, and too too heavy, ſuch as I never felt the like, and they make me greatly fear, how I ſhall be able to bear them, and ſubſiſt under them. Wherefore I earneſtly entreat thee, moſt dear Lord, to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151173:38"/> take off this burden, and free me of it.</hi> The Bridegroom anſwereth her: Tell me my beloved Spouſe, doth it ſeem equitable to you, that the Spouſe ſhould fare better then her Bridegroom, thou muſt firſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity in ſome meaſure follow him. And certainly it is altogether comely, juſt and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo tollerable, that the Spouſe ſhould endure ſomething, at leaſt for the love of her Bridegroom. When this the pleaſure of the Bridegroom is made known, the Spouſe is ſtricken with terrour, and trembling, ſaith to the Bridegroom. <hi>Oh! my Lord and Bridegroom, I beſeech you be not angry with me, for I am now ready to obey thee;</hi> Therefore ſuffer what thou pleaſeſt to fall upon me, I will through the aſſiſtance of thy grace bear all for thy ſake, willingly and contentedly. When the Bridegroom hears this, he conceives a greater love to his Spouſe. And therefore beſtows upon her yet a more excellent gift, namely, that all her performances, exerciſes, wayes, and all her works, yea, and at leaſt whatever ſhe does or leaves undone, although they be all good in themſelves, yet they ſeem to her ſelf wholly unſavoury. Furthermore, ſhe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts her whole time loſt, whatever ſhe ſpends it about, though that which ſhe doth
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151173:39"/> be good; and that in all ſhe offends the Bridegroom, and continually fears that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this liſe ſhe ſhall ſuffer grievous puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for all. Furthermore, this gift is granted her, that ſhe be had in deriſion by moſt, and that her whole life and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as meer folly be vilified and ſet at naught by men. But by this means the Spouſe becomes much weakned in her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; ſo that ſhe thinks every hour ſhe ſhall dye no other death. And whereas ſhe is yet tender, faint-hearted, and fearful, ſhe is exceeding terrified. Wherefore ſhe earneſtly calls upon her Bridegroom, ſaying. Why is it moſt ſweet Bridegroom, that thou leaveſt me in this ſad condition, when thou notwithſtanding knoweſt full well that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly undergo it, but it will coſt me my life. The Bridegroom anſwers her, Why how now my choſen Spouſe, if thou wilt go forth to meet the Bridegroom, it is equitable and congruous, that thou ſhouldſt at leaſt in ſome things at firſt follow him; and travail part of the journey he went. Whereas therefore the Bridegroom ſuffered death for the love of his Bride, and endured moſt direful torments, and innumerable pains 33 years, think you it not congruous to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and every way fitting, that the Spouſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151173:39"/> alſo out of love ſhould endure ſome hazard of death. Certainly, if your love were great &amp; faithful toward your Bridegroom, it would eaſily ſhut out all ſuch fear from you. The Spouſe fearing, ſuch or the like, anſwers from the Bridegroom, is ceaſed upon with excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great fear and ſhame: and ſpeaks thus from her moſt inward bowels, with heart and mouth to her Bridegroom. Now moſt loving Bridegroom, I fully underſtand that I have done unjuſtly and evilly: and I am even overcome with fear, and do grieve truly with my whole heart; becauſe I have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned my ſelf faithfully unto thee, even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death. And behold, hence-forward I commit my whole ſelf to thee; That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thy will and pleaſure is, the ſame may be mine, whether it be ſweet or whether it be bitter, whether it be health or whether it be ſickneſs, whether death or life, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be that thy pleaſure is ſhall come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, ſhall be welcome to me. And ſo for the future, I wholly renounce my own will; and ſo ſurrender and offer it up to thee, as never-more hereafter to re-call it or deſire it.</p>
                     <p>Thou alſo moſt merciful Bridegroom, do with me a ſinful wretch, whatever thou wilt, both in Time and in Eternity. For as
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151173:40"/> much as of me is, I plainly underſtand that I am unworthy that the earth ſhould bear me. When now the Bridegroom perceives ſo reſolved, ſo conſtant &amp; perfect a will in his Spouſe; What do you think he doth to his Spouſe? Even this, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> hath mercy on her; but how you will ask? Why thus? He will then firſt reach out to her an excellent and glorious Cup, namely this, That over and above all the preſſures, temptations and ſtraights in which already ſhe is held, he permits that far more, and far more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous then ever ſhe ſuffered before to fall upon her. The Spouſe by this time under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this to be the pleaſure of her Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, ſuffers all willingly and freely, for the love of him. And bowing her ſelf humbly to her Lord, ſaith; Even thus moſt dear Bridegroom is it moſt fitting and meet, that not what I will thou ſhouldſt will, but what thy Will and Pleaſure is that I ſhould will. Wherefore for thy ſake, I will freely and with a willing mind take off this Cup, and receive this gift of thine, let it torture and afflict my nature as much as it will; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, I accept of it as at thy hand. Whileſt therefore the Bridegroom in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Wiſdom beholds this will and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his Spouſe; ſhe is rendred above
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151173:40"/> meaſure dear unto him. So that even out of ſuperabundant love, he permits her to ſuffer through her whole nature by the ſaid Cup of pretious affliction given unto her, until ſhe be throughly purged and cleanſed from all her ſpots, ſins, and imperfections. But then he ſaith unto her. Ariſe now my beautiful and comely Spouſe, for now thou art all fair, and there is no ſpot in thee; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all looks upon her ſo amiably, and kindly, as is far above all Expreſſion.</p>
                     <p>After this the Eternal Father of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom cometh alſo to the nuptials, and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſaith to them: Ariſe quickly make haſte. It is time that they be led to the Temple, and joyned together in a marriage league. And taking both the Bridegroom, and the Bride, leads them both together to the Temple, and joyns them mutually to himſelf, and with ſo ſtrong and great a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual nuptial love doth couple and bind them one to the other; that neither in time, nor in eternity can they ever more be put aſunder, or ſeparated one from the other. Now whilſt theſe nuptials are celebrating, the Son the Bridegrom ſaith to his Father; Eternal and moſt loving Father, whom will it pleaſe you, ſhall be our Cup-bearer, and Comptroller of our nuptial Feaſts? The Father made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:151173:41"/> and ſaid: This office and buſineſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the Holy Ghoſt, and he ſhall be the Governour of the Feaſt that day. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently without any delay, that Magnificent, Higheſt, and Moſt adorable Cup-bearer gives the Spouſe to drink, and take off ſuch an overflowing Cup of Love, that ſhe is wholly overflowed, and drowned in Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and altogether flowes forth, and is diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and melted into her Bridegroom. And falling into an Exſtaſie, ſhe becomes ſo drunk even with over much Love, that ſhe looſeth and forgetteth her ſelf, and all other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, both ſuch as are in time, and ſuch as are in Eternity. For truly (beloved) who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever attaineth to theſe nuptials, the ſame then firſt is arrived at the very true ſolemnity of joys indeed, and of Eternal nuptials. And whoſoever is made ſuch a Spouſe, ſuch a one is become a true Worſhipper; adoring the Father in Spirit and Truth: <note place="margin">John 4:</note> and the ſame hath found peace and joy in the Holy Ghoſt. For verily in theſe nuptials there is joy upon joy: as alſo there the peace is greater, and Triumphant joy more abundant in one hour, then all Creatures whether in time, or in Eternity can make. For the joy, which the Spouſe here takes in her Bridegroom, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives from him, is ſuch, and ſo great, that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151173:41"/> no Reaſon, no Senſe can poſſibly underſtand it, attain to it, or be capable of it. At theſe words, One cryed out with a lond voyce: It is true, it is true, it is true. And immediatly fell to the Earth, as if he had been dead. At which ſight, a certain Woman ſpake aloud to the Doctor; give over Maſter Doctor, or elſe this man will give up the Ghoſt in our arms. The Doctor anſweared? Well dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, if it ſeems good to the Bridegroom to take away with him this Spouſe, we ought willingly to leave her to him. But be ye ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a little while, for I ſhall even now make an end.</p>
                     <p>Let us all (I beſeech you, dearly beloved) let us all with one conſent lift up our voyces unto Heaven, unto the Lord, imploring his mercy. For truly, it is a thing extreamly to be bewailed by us, that we ſhould be made ſuch Fools, ſo dull, and ſottiſh; as that, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding we are none of us ignorant, how we are all called the Spouſes of God; yet ſcarce one of us, or very rarely, hath the courage to hazard his Nature, in manfully following the Bridegroom, until he be found worthy to be made partaker, and taſte by experience ſomewhat at leaſt of the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and moſt pleaſant ſolemnization, of theſe ſupream Triumphs, and moſt happy nuptials.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151173:42"/> Verily, in theſe latter times there are but few ſuch found, as do in truth go forth to meet the Bridegroom; ſuch, as of old time there were many. Wherefore it exceedingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns every one, to examine, and ſeriouſly and diligently to try himſelf; and to have a vigilant care of himſelf: For now the time draws near, and is even at the door, when the greateſt part of men will indeed have Eyes, and yet ſee not, and Ears, and yet hear not.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore now, my dearly beloved, come on, let us all do our utmoſt endeavour to come to the experiencing of theſe moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, &amp; even too too happy nuptials. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> that I may purſue my purpoſe, &amp; come to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion; After that the Bridegroom and the Bride are gone aſunder, &amp; withdrawn each from other, &amp; the Bride again coming to her ſelf, perceives that ſhe is yet left in this time of exile, ſhe ſaith to her ſelf; Ah me miſerable wretch, am I here again? And begins to be ſomewhat ſad. But ſhe is now ſo modeſt, ſo ſunk into the depth of humility, and finally ſo perfectly, and fundamentally reſigned to her Bridegroom, that ſhe durſt in no meaſure think of the injoying, or deſiring his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, for ſhe very well know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s, that ſhe is altogether unworthy of it. Notwithſtanding
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151173:42"/> the Bridegroom neglects not ever now and then to have an Eye upon his fair beloved, and deareſt Bride, knowing full well that none can comfort her but himſelf. And now in the winding up of my Diſcourſe, let me give you this caution (dearly Beloved.) Let it not ſeem ſtrange unto you, what I have ſaid unto you touching the Diſcourſe, which the Bridegroom and the Bride have with one another. Certainly no man can believe, except he have had experience of it; what ſtrange kind, and unheard of Diſcourſes the Bride hath with the Bridegroom; Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Holy Scriptures alſo oft make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, how a loving and devoted Soul Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes with the Bridegroom, and in ſuch a manner, that her words hardly will bear ſenſe with them. Which alſo ſometimes happens even at this day; namely, that the Bride uſeth ſuch expreſſions to the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, that if any one heard them, he would certainly ſay, ſhe were either drunk or mad. But I fear (Beloved) I am too tedious.</p>
                     <p>God therefore and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt the true Bridegroom grant, that we may be all made his true Spouſes, and be able to go forth to meet him in true and great Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and deep and perfect reſignation of our
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151173:43"/> ſelves to him, to the Praiſe and Glory of the Almighty God.</p>
                     <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of certain wonderful Things, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fel ſome upon the Hearing the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Sermon, which afterwards were underſtood. From whence we may take notice, How great things God worketh by fit Inſtruments; namely, by the Sermon of any one Illuminated Mans, much more then by the Sermons of an hundred others.</head>
               <p>THIS Sermon being ended, the Maſter went into the Temple, diſpatched Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service, and adminiſtred the Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords Body to very many good men. But in the Garden of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtry, there remained ſitting above fourty men. Which thing the Layman had taken notice off. And when the Sacrament was ended, coming to the Doctor, he told him of it: and taking him with him, led him to the place, where he might ſee it. But in the mean time, whilſt the Maſter was admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Sacrament, all were riſen, except twelve, whom they found ſitting there ſtill.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151173:43"/> When the Maſter ſaw this, he ſaid to the Layman: Dear Son, what ſhall we do to theſe men? Then the Layman went to them, and touched, and jogged them one by one, but they felt nothing, and ſeemed to be no otherwiſe then dead. At which the Maſter did not a little wonder, for he had never ſeen any ſuch thing in the leaſt before. And ſaith again to the Layman; Think you Son that theſe men are dead? The Layman ſmiling ſaid, if they be dead, it is the fault of you, and the Bridegroom.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Maſter.</label> If the Bridegroom have a hand with me in the buſineſs, we ſhall eaſily find a Remedy for this evil.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> You need not at all doubt Sir, but that all theſe men ſhall live yet in time; and I could wiſh, that you would ſpeak to the Holy Virgins of this Monaſtery, that they would cauſe them to be carryed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the firſt Cloiſters of their Monaſtery, to ſome warm place, leaſt by reaſon of the damp ground they ſhould catch harm. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly it was done; the Virgins very modeſtly commanding them to be carried into warm Rooms: and they told the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, that they alſo had one of their Siſters rapped into an exſtaſie, and lying upon her Bed, whither they had carryed her as one
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:151173:44"/> dead. The Maſter anſwered them, I beſeech you (Beloved) be not troubled at this thing; but when any of them comes to themſelves, give them (if they will take it) ſome kind of warm broth. The Virgins anſwered him, That they would willingly do. And ſo the Doctor together with the Layman departed, and went together to the Doctors Cell: Where the Layman ſaid to the Doctor. What think you, Reverend Sir, did ever the like matter befal you ſince you were born? you ſee now, what great things God doth work by a fit Inſtrument. And I doubt not, but very many more will be ſenſible of this your Sermon, and what was done at it: For they will tell one another. Wherefore I ſhall like it well, if you pleaſe, that you would ſuffer theſe your weak Sons and Daughters to reſt a while. For truly, this Sermon will find them work enough for a long time. But I verily think many would reap much benefit, if you would likewiſe (God permitting) Preach to the ſecular men. For now during this time of Lent, they will more readily run to Sermons. And I believe, very many will flock together the more, becauſe of this Sermon, which you preached to day.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Maſter.</label> If you advice me to it (dear
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151173:44"/> Son) I will willingly follow your counſel. And (as I remember) this next Sabbath day, is the Feaſt of the Virgin <hi>S. Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> And pray what is the Goſpel appointed for that day?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Maſter.</label> It is concerning the Woman taken in adultry, and brought to Chriſt. But whatever the Goſpel be for that day, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to ſtick only to that; But will eaſily take from thence ſome ſentence or other, which ſhall be the ſcope of my whole Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; and from it I will take occaſion as Divine Grace ſhall aſſiſt me, to ſet before Mens Eyes their ſins and Iniquities. Neither do I much care, what becomes of me for ſo doing. Though I eaſily believe that firſt this will be my portion; my Brethren will do what they can to expel me out of the Monaſtery; for I am reſolved neither to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, nor any body elſe: but will ſimply ſpeak the naked truth, as the Lord ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able me: neither will I balk that, though I ſhould be therefore to ſuffer death.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Layman.</label> Truly (I believe Sir) for theſe two or three hundred years, or more by paſt, there hath not been ſo much need, to ſpeak the naked Truth ſimply and ſeriouſly, as now in theſe our days. Wherefore be not at all
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151173:45"/> moved with whatever can happen. For if you be not ſuffered to abide here, you may be ſome where elſe: and whereſoever you be, God will in no wiſe forſake you. The Maſter therefore gave order to one, that at the end of his Sermon he ſhould give notice to the People, that he intended to Preach the next Sabbath day, which was conſecrated to St. <hi>Gartrude.</hi> When that day came, a very great multitude of Men of divers ranks came together, to hear the Doctors Sermon. Who coming at the time appointed; Thus began his Diſcourſe.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="sermon">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Sermon of the Doctors Preached to the People, in which he ſharply reproves Sin.</head>
                     <p>VVHat ſhall I ſay, or where ſhall I begin my Diſcourſe (Dearly Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) ſeeing 'tis obvious to every Eye, how ill it is with us in many things, and unleſs we amend our Lives, undoubtedly things will grow worſe, and worſe, and more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous? But before I enter upon my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, I earneſtly beg this of you all; that none of you would take that grievouſly, which I ſhall ſay unto you. For truly, it is more needful at this time to ſpeak the Truth
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151173:45"/> plainly, and openly, then it hath been any time theſe two or three hundred years, or upwards. Whereupon I have reſolved with my ſelf to reprove the Faults of us all in general, and not at all to flatter any man; but without any daubing, obſcure gloſſes, or comments, to ſpeak ſimply and nakedly, whatever the Lord ſhall teach, or ſuggeſt to me: being ready for the Love of God, to undergo any thing that ſhall be laid upon me for this cauſe. But if I ſhall be hindred by the ſhortneſs of the time, to finiſh now what I have to ſay, I ſhall at another time (if li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty be granted me) make an end of it. Truly, I have purpoſed to handle ſo many things in this Sermon, that I will neither meddle with the Goſpel for the day, nor ſpeak any thing of bleſſed <hi>Gartrude,</hi> to whom the day is conſecrated, nor mingle any La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine ſentences in my Diſcourſe, that ſo I may have the longer time to ſpeak what I intend. I have only taken for my Text a Verſe or two out of this days Goſpel, upon which I will only inſiſt. The Words are theſe;</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Phariſees bringing a Woman taken in Adultry to our Lord, ſet her in the midſt, and accuſed her, that ſhe ought to be ſtoned; The Lord ſaid unto them, He that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Sin among you, let him caſt the firſt ſtone.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:151173:46"/>
                     <p>When they heard this, they went one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another out of the Temple. Verily (Beloved) if in theſe our days, our Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſhould ſpeak the ſame Words to us Chriſtians; I verily believe, very few of us could remain behind, who ought not to go forth. And leaſt whilſt I am reproving others for their faults, I ſhould ſeem to paſs by my own, and the ſins of our Order; I will begin with my ſelf, and my Brethren, the Preachers and Confeſſors. How many think you of us, would ſtay behind upon theſe Words of our Saviour, who being conſcious to themſelves of no ſin, would not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to go forth? Truly we are called, and accompted poor, and live upon the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Crucifix, that is, upon the Almes of the faithful. But how worthily in all things we anſwer this our calling, the Lord knows, and the Devil knows. Truly I fear there are very few among us, who in hearing confeſſions do purely love God, and aim at his Glory: Of which thing this is an evident Argument, that for the moſt part, we are more ready to hear the confeſſions of the Rich, than of the Poor. And that this is ſo, is plain by this. If any ſuch of us be taking the confeſſion of any Poor man; and word be brought us that ſuch a Lord, or
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151173:46"/> ſuch a Lady is come, we preſently ariſe in haſt, and diſmiſſing the Poor man, hie us away to my Lord, or to my Lady. And why is this? but becauſe we are covetous, and love honour, and are tickled, if we can make our braggs, that more Lords and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies make their confeſſions to us, then to others: in the mean time we make mention of the Poor Saints. But how, and in what manner we be have our ſelves towards thoſe Rich ones, God the righteous Judge knoweth. Certainly it is our duty to teach them the way of Truth, and uprightneſs, and in what manner they ought to lead their lives; and not, when they deſire to have their wicked and unlawful cuſtomes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulged, and permitted, to frame and invent many ſubtil Gloſſes, and ſhifts, and tell them their leud cuſtoms are not repugnant to the Scriptures. Nevertheleſs we tell them, that which is falſe. For the Scripture no where ſaith, that covetouſneſs, pride, luxury, or the like ſins may be indulged, or permitted; Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is this any other than the inventions and council of the malignant one. Wherefore (my Beloved) thoſe of us, as are ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours, do ſhew unto you not the way of truth, but the way of perdition: and ſo we firſt run head-long into the Pit of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151173:47"/> perdition, and then alſo lead you along with us into the ſame; there is onely this difference, that we ſhall be thruſt lowermoſt, and you caſt upon us into thoſe pains. But though ye rich men are not ſo deeply plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into thoſe pains as we; yet your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſhall not therefore be the better; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your own Reaſon, and Conſcience of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tells you, that we in no wiſe ſhew unto you the right, and ſafe way. Further more, we in duty ought alſo (beloved) when we are in the Pulpit, to preach unto you the right way, and in few words, without ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and gloſſing, to ſhew unto you the very truth. Which if it ever were needful to do, is now much more needful. But alas! the moſt of us, are too too fooliſh, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and ſtand more in awe of men, than of God. Now the reaſon of this is, that in theſe our times, matters are come to that paſs, that if any of us will ſpeak the very truth, he will hardly be tollerated almoſt in any Monaſtery, nor ſuffered to Preach: and preſently another ſhall be put into his place, who will reject, and confute whatever the former hath ſaid.</p>
                     <p>Truly (Beloved) things are not right a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us; therefore I will not be partial, but ſpeak the Truth. Nay, rather I will
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151173:47"/> (as the Lord ſhall enable me) ſimply ſet before all our eyes in general, of what ſtate or condition ſoever we be, our vices, and failings: let what will befal me therefore; I will endure it all willingly, for the love of my Lord God. He of you (Beloved) who is without ſin, (if there be ſuch a one) let him caſt the firſt ſtone at them I have mentioned. What I have hitherto ſpoken, may, at the firſt view, ſeem as if I had onely aimed at my Brethren of our Order. But my intention was nothing leſs, than onely to mark out them: but my reproof was dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted againſt all thoſe, together with our ſelves, who hear confeſſions, and are Preachers of the Word: whether they be Paſtors, or Prieſts, or of ſome Religious Order, of what rank ſoever they be, to whom the aforeſaid Authority is committed, and given: To all theſe (I would have you to underſtand) was my diſcourſe dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. Here now I ſhould ſay ſomething of the Biſhops and other Prelates of great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and Power, who hold many Churches. But I ſuppoſe here is not any one preſent. Nevertheleſs, leaſt any ſhould think, that if I paſs over theſe in ſilence, I do it for fear of them, or upon ſome other conſideration, as if I would flatter, and ſeek
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:151173:48"/> to curry favour; I ſhall (I ſay therefore) ſay ſomething of them: and there will not be wanting ſome, or other it may be, that will go and tell them what I ſay; which thing I ſhall not at all miſlike, nor be troubled at. Certainly, in what Province ſoever any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick is, the Biſhop is the Paſtor of that Province, how far ſoever the bounds of his Juriſdiction or Dioceſs extends. He is, I ſay the Paſtor, and Head of his Biſhoprick, and that, for to feed his People; and to take all vigilant care, that the whole Flock committed to his charge, be trained up in the due obſervation of Chriſtian Religion and Chriſtian Ordinances. But alas! when as now for the moſt part the Paſtors are blind, no wonder, if their ſheep go aſtray, and become a prey for Wolves. But what need I uſe many words, when you eaſily perceive what I hint at? I fear truly, that many of our great Prieſts, and potent Prelates, who hold at one time many Churches, are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe held and entangled themſelves in many, and grievous ſins; and are ſometimes even worſe than thieves, and robbers; for theſe onely rob men of their Goods, but theſe wicked, and unworthy Prieſts, rob and plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der even God of his Goods; for all Church livings are Gods, and his Almes, which of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:151173:48"/> right he hath given to none, but to ſuch, as are careful to ſpend them in his ſervice. But when it comes to paſs, that ſuch a Prieſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with many Churches, dyes, what kind of Will and Teſtament leaveth he to his Heirs? Verily, a lamentable one; for the ſame way, which he walked in himſelf, doth he ſhew unto his Heirs. For his Heirs greedily catch his Goods, and haſten with them to the ſame place of Perdition, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he is gone before. At leaſt if they dye without Reſtitution, I am not able in a ſhort Diſcourſe to expreſs, how dangerous their eſtate and condition is. <hi>But let him who is without ſin among you, caſt the firſt ſtone at them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And now in the next place, I muſt have a word to the Secular Prieſts, of inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our rank; many of whom (I fear) do too too ſinfully, and dangerouſly lead their lives: Plainly, whatever Prieſt follows the courſe of Gameſters, and Fornicators, ſuch a one is worſe than <hi>Judas,</hi> who betrayed our Lord and Saviour: as it may eaſily be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
                     <p>For <hi>Judas</hi> was a thief, a ſlippery fellow, a betrayer of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. But a Prieſt, he hath an Eccleſiaſtical Benefice, which is Gods, who therefore hath granted
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151173:49"/> it to him, that he ſhould perform his Office, and permits him to take of it what is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for life, and what he cannot without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience want; but if any thing remain over and above, ſeeing that is totally Gods; if he reſtore not to God in his poor Members, but ſpends it upon ſome other unlawful uſe; ſuch a one truly commits a worſe theft than <hi>Judas</hi> did. For ſuch a Prieſt conſumes the Goods of his God at Dice, and divers other wayes doth waſt the Almes given to the poor, truly worſe than <hi>Judas</hi> did. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, ſuch a Prieſt with the ſame impure hands, fears not to handle his God upon the Altar, with which he hath touched filthily a vile Harlot; and kiſſeth her with the ſame mouth, by which God entred; and gives her his heart, which he ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote to God alone; and at laſt breaks his Vow, and Oath, which he made unto God, and therewith betrayes God, when he joyns himſelf to a woman, when as he ought to be united to God onely: neither doth it ſuffice him, to do this (as <hi>Judas</hi> did) but once, but he doth it often. Truly, <hi>Judas</hi> did but once receive the Lord in the Sacrament; and peradventure he neither was conſecrated, as is the Prieſt, nor had made a Vow of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, as doth the Prieſt. From hence
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151173:49"/> therefore do you your ſelves now judge (Beloved) whether ſuch a Prieſt be not worſe than even <hi>Judas</hi> himſelf. Verily, I am ſufficiently afraid, that many now adayes out-ſtrip <hi>Judas.</hi> But let all ſuch (I beſeech them) conſider the frailty of their condition, and uncertainty of their life, and from their hearts amend their lifes; which of all things doth moſt concern them. Truly, I cannot but extreamly wonder, that any wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man can be guilty of ſo much preſumption, as to dare to ſuffer her ſelf once to be touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any Prieſt. But now if Secular Prieſts, who are ſubject to the foreſaid vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, are worſe than <hi>Judas</hi> the Traytor: we, who are called the Religious, and live in Sacred Monaſtical Orders, if we commit the like, we certainly are yet far more wicked. But if a Prelate commit ſuch like, his ſins are yet more grievous. If a Biſhop, he ſins yet more notorious. If laſtly the Pope, his ſins of all others were the worſt, and moſt heavy. For by how much the higher the ſtation is, by ſo much the more grievous is the fall, and greater the fault. But if a Virgin dedicated to God, a Monaſtical Virgin, ſhall commit any of theſe things, ſhe doth exceeding enormouſly ſin. For ſuch a one ought both in body and Soul
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:151173:50"/> to conform her ſelf according to the example of the Virgin Mother. For as our Lady the Glorious Virgin, brought forth her only Son without any violation of her Virginity; ſo all the conſecrated Virgins have made a Vow to follow the example of the Moſt Bleſſed Mother, in all chaſtity; that they may be the better enabled to breed, and bring forth God, the Son of God continually in their hearts. <hi>But who is there here with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin? If ſuch a one there be, let him firſt caſt a ſtone at all theſe, I have mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But now whilſt I ſtay over-long in repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving onely Spiritual Perſons, or the Clergy; you Seculars and Lay-people may ſuppoſe I have forgot you: Therefore now I muſt bring you forth into view alſo. For nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are you without ſin, but even as we, ſo are ye in many things reproveable. But there is no reaſon, why any one ſhould caſt all that is ſaid, upon another; but rather examine himſelf, and his own heart; where I believe (if he do it as he ought) he will find ſo much buſineſs at home, that he will hardly be mindful of others faults. But I beſeech you (Beloved) do not take grievouſly thoſe things, which I am now about to ſpeak. Truly, I ſhall begin with the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151173:50"/> Judges and Magiſtrates of this City. You therefore my Lords the Judges &amp; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, (if any of you be here) tell me I beſeech you, how ſtands it, and what agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is there between you and God? Ye your ſelves know that ye admit no man into your Order, except he be of ſufficient age, and have his lawful Wife. And this you do juſtly enough. But why this is done, ye do not in the mean time well underſtand. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore in old time, the antient Judges did ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry carefully and with much prudence enact this; that no young men ſhould be admitted in their Order; but ſuch as had firſt arrived at a Juſt age; that ſo in that time they might a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ain to the knowledge of the Civil, Imperial, and Provincial Laws; and learn the Laws of their Anceſtors, and Statutes of their Countrey. And when they had ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at a fitting age, and had thoroughly learned all theſe Lawes; If they were alſo Juſt men, and endowed with the fear of the Lord; ſo that they might be accounted worthy of truſt, and fit for ſuch an Office; then at laſt did the Antients chuſe them, and receive them into their Number. That all, who are of your Order, ought to have lawful Wives, it was therefore ordained, leaſt they ſhould deſire in their hearts or
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:151173:51"/> minds any other women, beſides their own Wives. Here now, I beſeech you, my Lords examine your ſelves, whether you be exact Immitators of your Anceſtors. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it doth not ſo appear to me. For you ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit many into your Order for favour and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection onely; and admit ſuch to ſit upon the Judgement Seat, who, as it is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known, have no fear of God; love ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and receive money where ever they can get it, caring not at all whether lawfully or unlawfully. But truely ſuch gifts and rewards, which are thus received, whilſt they are in Judgement, do ſubvert, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert Judgement and Juſtice.</p>
                     <p>Furthermore, you receive Adulterers into your Number, which, yet is altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, and in ſpecial manner forbidden, that ſuch ſhould be admitted to ſit in Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; whoſe lives are contrary to God, and good Lawes. And for this cauſe oftentimes falſe, and unjuſt Judgements are paſſed; which doubtleſs the Lord God, the Supream Judge, will heavily revenge at the laſt day, upon all thoſe, who have given them. For the Lord himſelf hath appointed Juſtice; and Judgement is his. If any one therefore turn Gods Juſtice, into Injuſtice; he will certainly not ſuffer it long to paſs unrevenged.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151173:51"/> Behold my Lords, ye that are Judges and Rulers of the People, I have choſen to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with you; becauſe you hold the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Power of Judicature. If you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reform and amend the Supream Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories, of which ye are Preſidents; the inferiour will eaſily after your example be reformed: becauſe your Authority will ſway with them, and bring it to paſs. But if there be neglect on your part in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; what ever is done amiſs in inferiour Courts, will be charged upon you, as being moſtly the cauſe of it. Believe me, your condition is very dangerous, except you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend your lifes. For doubleſs Juſtice is no ſmall matter in the ſight of God; but is a buſineſs full of difficulty. And we ſee in the Old Teſtament, how God was wont grievouſly to revenge unjuſt Judgements, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, and Pride: And doubtleſs he doth the ſame at this day; although we are grown ſo ſottiſh, and ſtupid, as not to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it. Beloved, if it be not burdenſome to you, I will briefly tell you a ſtrange, and terrible thing; namely, how great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, and grievous ſins had their riſe from one act of Adultery, within theſe few years. Neither will I tell you a Dream, or a Fable; but what I my ſelf know to be true. When
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151173:52"/> I were in the thirtieth year of my age, and by the Order of my Superiours followed my Studies in a certain Town; I be came fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly acquainted with two Citizens of the place. They were both young men, and very rich Merchants. Theſe two loved one the other entirely, and managed their Trade in common: they had both of them young Wiſes much alike; who did alſo no leſs love one another. And when it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened at any time, that either of them went from home about buſineſs; (ſuch truſt and confidence had they in each other) he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes committed his Wife, his Houſe, and all his Goods to the others care. It fell out, that after I had been acquainted with them about a year; One of their Wives, came to me at a certain time, and privately told me, with a mournful voice, and many tears; That ſhe had been, of a long time, an heinous ſinner, and that ſhe ſhould be no better than a fire-brand of Hell. Which when ſhe had ſaid, ſhe ſhed ſuch abundance of tears, that ſhe could not ſpeak one word more: I being moved with her tears, and ſuffering with her, in her ſorrow, I deſired her to lay open the cauſe of ſo great a ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, promiſing her, by Gods aſſiſtance, (whoſe mercy I told her was infinite) to give
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151173:52"/> her faithful Council. At laſt, ſhe taking heart, ſhe ſaid, Ah Sir, my Daughter N. is not ligitimate, but begot in adultery by my Husbands Friend. For when, above five years ago, my Husband was a great while from home, his Friend upon a certain time, abuſing that too much confidence, which you know, we have in one another; whilſt we were familiarly converſing toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, fell at laſt in the ſin of adultery with me; and of him I conceived my foreſaid Daughter N. Furthermore to aggravate my damnation, I never made confeſſion of this ſin, after this my fall; but like the Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Judas,</hi> have nine times ſince recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with polluted heart and mouth, the moſt Holy Body of our Lord. When I heard this, I wiſhed her, if ſhe deſired right advice, to tell me the naked truth, whether ſhe had more then once layn with that adulterer; and alſo, whether he knew that her Daughter N. was his, or no. She anſwered, that they had but once (ſhe thanked God) committed that ſin, and that they had both ſo much repented them of it, that if it could be, they would give any money it were undone. Neither could he poſſibly ever know that N. was his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; becauſe ſhe for certain reaſons had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151173:53"/> kept that ſecret to her ſelf. I adviſed her therefore firſt, that ſhe ſhould find out ſome way, whereby ſhe might ſafely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the whole matter to her Husband. To which ſhe anſwered, that ſhe durſt in no wiſe do that. For, if my Husband (ſaid ſhe) ſhould come to the knowledge of this, I am certain, that he would either kill the adulterer together with me, or elſe be kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by him; and ſo this thing would ſtraight be ſpread abroad among the vulgar. Then ſaid I, if you dare not attempt this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fel; yet at leaſt do this by all means; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure that your illigitimate Daughter be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in ſome Monaſtery, and let her in no caſe have poſſeſſion of any part of your Husbands eſtate, together with his true Heirs, to their dammage, and the eternal damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your Souls; for if ſhe ſhould in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit any part of your Husbands eſtate, ſhe would poſſeſs it unlawfully. And you may tell your Husband, that you have devoted that Daughter to Religion, and be urgent with him, to ſuffer you to fulfil your Vow. Accordingly the woman did very oft en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour it; and I backing her, tryed by many reaſons to perſwade her Husband; but all our endeavours were in vain. At laſt I again told her plainly, that if ſhe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151173:53"/> would deliver her own Soul, ſhe muſt find out ſome means, in the ſweeteſt manner ſhe could poſſibly, to declare the whole matter to her Husband; that ſo he might not take the buſineſs ſo heinouſly, as ſhe fear'd; and this, before her Daughter be diſpoſed of in marriage; that ſo at laſt ſhe might be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from this dangerous and troubleſome remorſe of Conſcience. But while ſhe was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oo long in ſuſpence; It fell out that the two Merchants, by the Mediation and counſel of Friends, made up a match between the ones Son, and the others ſuppoſed Daughter; but indeed between the Brother and Siſter, who being thus inceſtuouſly joyned, wonderfully loved one the other. When I beheld ſo great iniquity, out of pitty ſuffering with theſe miſerable People; I tryed divers wayes, if by any means they might be ſeperated the one from the other. But when I ſaw I a ſailed nothing, and that the fore-named Virgin N. was with child by her Brother, her Husband; and being called home by the commands of my Superiours; I counſelled her, that had committed the firſt Sin and Adultery, that ſhe ſhould diſcover in confeſſion her whole ſorrow to one Brother N. a pious and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man, and follow his advice. And ſo I departed.</p>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:151173:54"/>
                     <p>But how unhappily theſe matters after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſucceeded with them, (as that Brother wrote me word) I am hardly able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs. And truly, all this Story is of my own knowledge. Therefore how many probably may there be of Brothers and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and other near kindred, which I know nothing of, which may in other places be joyned together in Matrimony. Truly, I fear, that there is a certain Father (which verily is not fit to be ſpoken of) that doth commit Inceſt and Adultry with his own Daughter. Plainly (Beloved) it can not be ſpoken how many and grievous ſins have their birth and original out of Luxury and Adultry. Take it for certain, that Adultry is an enormous crime, and very odious to God. Therefore hath Hell enlarged it's mouch without bound. Believe me an Adulterer, or Adultereſs is in a manner worſe then a Thief or Robber. For a Thief, and a Robber do but take away a man's temporal Goods. But an Adulterer, or Adultereſs, do commit a more heinous crime by committing Adultry. For God himſelf inſtituted Matrimony, and therefore it is properly His, and He himſelf doth ſo ſtrongly joyn twain mutually toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in all faithfulneſs, that they are called one Body, and ought not to be guilty of the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151173:54"/> leaſt unfaithfulneſs one to the other, ſince they have both vowed and promiſed to God, that they would conſtantly be faithful the one to the other. A Thief therefore (as I ſaid) and a Robber takes away a man's Goods. But an Adulterer and Adultereſs incur the guilt of perjury, and therefore ſteal that which belongeth to God, and aſmuch as in them is, ſpoil and rob him. For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, ſacred Wedlock is ordained of God himſelf, that it might be his; and that men in much faithfulneſs and ſanctity might beget Children; to this end, that his Kingdom might be filled. Hence therefore now you your ſelves gather, whither Adultry be not far worſe then Theft and Rapine; when as Adulterers ſteal that, which is Gods: But Thieves &amp; Robbers only take away what is mans. Wherefore (Beloved) beware of Adultry, becauſe it is a grievous and enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous wickedneſs. Truly, If I would go about to lay open all the dangers and evills ſpringing out of Adultry, this whole day would hardly ſuffice, and yet I fear I have already been to tedious. I ſhould now ſpeak of Pride, of covetous men, of Soldiers, &amp; their Comrades, and Wives, of handy crafts men, and their Wives; but the time doth not permit. Truly, I have yet many things,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151173:55"/> which I ſhall ſay in their due time, except I be ſilenced from preaching. But I warn you beloved, let not any one hit another in the Teeth with theſe things which ye have heard, becauſe I have only touched the vices of ſome. For we are all guilty and obnoxious to ſin. But if there be any one here without Sin, let him firſt caſt a ſtone at them, whom I have mentioned. Believe me, as things are with us at preſent, it doth exceedingly concern us, that with what ſpeed poſſible, we ſhould amend our lives. Otherwiſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we ſo do; there are ſome among you, who may live till that time, wherein God Almighty may permit ſome grievous, and unuſual diſtreſs, and preſſure to happen to men. But ariſe now, and let us pray the Lords Prayer, and repeat the Angels ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How after this Sermon, the Maſter was forbidden by his Brethren to Preach again.</head>
               <p>AFter this Sermon, all the People of the City did talk much, and variouſly of the Maſter; ſome praiſed him, ſome diſpraiſed him: but the greater part did commend him, ſaying, He is certainly a good man,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151173:55"/> and devout towards God, who fears no man, but ſpeaks the very meer truth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and all others. But his Brethren pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after this Sermon, being met together in the Chapter-Room, unanimouſly conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that he ſhould be wholly ſilenced from Preaching: and they ſtudiouſly enough en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to bring it about, that they might ſend him away to another Monaſtery of their Order. Which when the Rulers, and chief men of the City found out; they went to thoſe Monks, and intreated them to grant Licenſe to the Maſter again to Preach: and likewiſe inquired of them, what fault they found in him, that they ſhould prohibit him from preaching, Who anſwered, He hath offended our beſt friends, and turned them from us. To which the Lords ſaid, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that ye have no better Friends certainly in this City then we; who can better take care of your affairs, and be more helpful to you then we. Therefore we fear that ye rather take it ill, that he publickly repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved you. But he reproved us alſo, and yet we take it not ill. Truly, ye ought rather at any price to purchaſe ſuch a man, as he is; who dares ſpeak the Truth to men; and as it ought to be, fears not the face of any man. So therefore out of reſpect to the Lords, and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151173:56"/> for their ſakes, It was not only permitted to the Maſter, to remain there, but alſo to Preach again. Afterwards the Maſter was intreated by the ſecular men, to Preach again another publick Sermon to them. He told them, he would do as they deſired, if the Lord gave him leave, the very next Lords day after the ninth. Now that Lords day was <hi>Judica,</hi> or the Paſſion of our Lord in <hi>Lent.</hi> And when the appointed day and hour was come, a very great multitude of common People came together; thither alſo came the Maſter, and thus began his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="sermon">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Maſters ſecond Sermon to the vulgar People.</head>
                     <p>THE Goſpel for this preſent day, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, is that, where the Lord ſaith to the multitudes, and to the chief Prieſts: <hi>Who among you convinceth me of Sin? If I ſay the Truth, why do ye not believe me? He that is of God, heareth the Words of God; For this cauſe ye hear not, becauſe ye are not of God.</hi> This Goſpel is long, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I hope moſt of you have heard it of your Paſtors to day; omitting it, I do make my Diſcourſe ſo much the ſhorter. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:151173:56"/> I begin to obtain Grace, let us call upon the Mother of Mercy, and all Grace, ſaying <hi>Ave Mary,</hi> &amp;c. Truly (Beloved) of right, when as to day, the Lords-day after the Lords Paſſion is Celebrated, I ought to Preach of the Paſſion: but I have ſo many things to ſpeak of, that that cannot be done at this time. For it is exceeding ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that we ſhould be ſpoke to of our ſins and failings. Nevertheleſs, if it may be commodiouſly done, I have purpoſed upon ſome convenient day this week, to Preach a Sermon of the venerable Sacrament; who namely have right to come unto it, and who not: and what it is hindreth them, who ought not to come. Afterwards alſo, I ſhall make a Sermon upon the moſt bitter Paſſion of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And indeed at this time, Beloved, I can ſay nothing to ye, unleſs I do ſpeak of the Community by their ſeveral Names and Titles. Wherefore alſo I would have you take this advice, that if any be here, to whom my diſcourſe ſhall not belong, let not them wreſt it as ſpoken to them; neither let them judge them, to whom peradventure it ſhall belong; but give God thanks, that he hath preſerved them from evil: But they, who ſhall underſtand them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be guilty, and whom my diſcourſe
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:151173:57"/> ſhall note, let them the more ſpeedily repent, and amend their lives. For this will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly neceſſary for them to do. This common true ſaying is found in almoſt every man's mouth; when we ſay that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> did exceeding wickedly, whilſt they followed the Devil, and tranſgreſſed the Commandment of the Lord their God. But if any one rightly did weigh it, how many (do we think) would he find now a dayes entangled in more grievous ſins, then <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> were? Certainly, every raſh, and ſwaggering Soldier, and his proud, and laſcivious Wife, do commit far more and greater evils, then <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> did. <hi>Eve</hi> indeed followed the Devil, and violated the Command of God. <hi>Adam</hi> alſo had reſpect to the Woman, and being willing to pleaſe her, he tranſgreſſed the precept of God. But preſently for the violation of this one command, they were both driven out of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe: and in ſuch a manner hath the wrath of Divine vengeance raged againſt them, and all their poſterity; that from that time, for the ſpace of five thouſand years, it ſuffered none to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven. And in the mean while <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> were compelled ſo long in the Limbo of Hell, to wait in expectation, until that full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:151173:57"/> of time came, wherein God the Father did vouchſafe to deliver them by his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son.</p>
                     <p>Truly (Beloved) I know that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> never neglected, but this one command; neither have I found in Scripture that they committed any other grievous ſin. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Almighty God hath ſo ſeverely &amp; hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly revenged upon them this one ſin; there is no cauſe certainly, why theſe proud, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſt, and vain Women do diſcommend them for many things, and accuſe them of many crimes. For verily be certain of this; if theſe Women go on in thoſe courſes, and actions, in which at preſent they live; I know not what will become of them. For they, not once only as <hi>Eve</hi> did, do tranſgreſs the Divine Commandment, but too too oft, in divers manners, at divers times, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Wherefore ye proud, fooliſh, and raſh Women, repent at laſt, I beſeech you: eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince ye know that the Lord of Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, whom ye offend by your iniquities hath ſo grievouſly taken vengeance upon <hi>Eve</hi> for ſin; yea alſo, and doth yet daily even too ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely take vengeance; as ye in the pains and diſtreſſes of child-bearing learn by your own experience. Repent, Repent, I ſay, ye Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men beloved in Chriſt. Otherwiſe except
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151173:58"/> ye ſo do, certain it is ye lead too too dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous a Liſe. And truly, it is a thing much to be bewailed, and a thing exceeding per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious and dangerous, that we, who attend upon the hearing of confeſſions, ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nive at ſuch things in you, whereby we are expoſed to as great danger as your ſelves. But your Husbands ſtand in greater danger, who imitate <hi>Adam,</hi> in indulging, conniving, and permitting you not once, but frequently to play the <hi>Eves.</hi> But hear me thou, who ever art ſuch a Husband, ſuch an <hi>Adam;</hi> Certainly, God hath not committed unto thee thy <hi>Eve,</hi> for this reaſon, that thou ſhouldeſt ſuffer her ſo oft to violate his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands: but rather for this cauſe hath he given her unto thee, that thou ſhouldeſt keep her, and take ſuch care of her, as not to ſuffer her to neglect ſo much as one precept. But now thou doſt very carefully regard her, who, when thou oughteſt to hinder ſin, art a helper of her to commit ſin. But whilſt you connive at thoſe evils, which ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth, you your ſelf are not innocent, but are partaker of her ſins, and ſo oft trangreſs the Divine Commandment. I exceedingly fear (Beloved) that at this time there may be found ſome Conſeſſors, who fear not to adminiſter the Holy Sacraments to very
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151173:58"/> many, both Men and Woman, whom not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they know to lye in ſome mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſins. And moſt of theſe, as I fear, at the end of their lives, are drowned in the depths of diſpair, and ſo incur the miſeries of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual damnation. For the Devils are very buſie about ſuch like worldly men, when they come to dye. For they grievouſly ſet before them all the ſins, which ever they committed. And what heart, think ye can thoſe wretches have then, when they have their whole life long been given to this fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacious World; and when the Devils are ſo exceeding ſubtile, and full of craft to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive? Now therefore, dearly Beloved, if any of you know themſelves guilty in any of theſe things, let them bluſh (I beſeech you) before God and Men, and make haſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form themſelves. For it is certain, that many Jews and Pagans are not a little ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized at your lives. Yea, verily the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, when they hear that Men and Women among us are cloathed ſo ſhamefully, and immodeſtly; they, as I have been informed by thoſe that heard them, ſay thus: Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians probably are not true men, becauſe they go cloathed ſo like beaſts; but perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture have ſomething in them of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of beaſts. And ye all know, that the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151173:59"/> Jews dwell among us here in our Country: Who, when they hear (and they hear it but too often) how in juriouſly we treat God by our impious and horrible ſwearing; ſay, as it hath been told me by others, nay, and as I have heard my ſelf, when upon a time I ſpake with them concerning our Chriſtian Faith: they thus ſay. Can we believe that he is our God, whom you ſay is your God? Certainly, we are thus perſwaded, that if your God were of ſo great power; he would in no wiſe permit, nor ſuffer it to go unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; that you oft do ſo impiouſly deal with him with wrathful minds, too oft fwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and for-ſwearing: Doubtleſs if he were God, he would never bear it. Wherefore ye need not doubt, but ye unmeaſurably ſin, whoever give the reigns to your tongues thus impiouſly to ſwear. Believe me, God will not ſuffer this long to go unrevenged, but either here, or in the World to come, where ſins are too too bitterly puniſhed; will take vengeance on you for it. And you unchaſt Women, who wear ſo laſcivious and wicked habits, take it for certain, that the moſt pure and great God will ſpeedily puniſh terribly the wantonneſs of your Garments: for he will not long endure it. Where is now that honeſt, chaſt, modeſt, and well-ordered
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151173:59"/> Converſation of yours? How hath the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil robbed you ſo of it almoſt all? I fear, I fear truly, that God the juſt Judge will call you to a ſevere account for your impudent and ſinful manner of life. For he himſelf ſaith: If a Man look upon a Woman, or a Woman upon a Man, if one luſt after the other, he hath then committed Adultry in his heart; and now death is compleated, though yet the act be not done. Whither I pray ſhall a man turn his Eyes; where he may not behold you, O ye ſcornful Women? Alas! your condition on both ſides is too too dangerous, Ye are always blaming <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> becauſe they broke one only Commandment; though they have for that tranſgreſſion ſuffered ſo many evils even to death, yea and after death: But it were better that inſtead of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> you did reprove &amp; blame your ſelves; ſeeing it is to be feared, that ye have oftner by far tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the Commandments of God than they. But whereas in this Diſcourſe I have only mentioned Military men &amp; their wives; let not therefore any one think, that I inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to mark only them. For truly, I would put to rebuke all what ever, both thoſe that are above, and thoſe that are below the rank of Soldiers; namely, Merchants and their
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:151173:60"/> Wives, and in brief all thoſe that are upon the fore-mentioned accompt blameable, of what rank or quality ſoever they be.</p>
                     <p>Again, it is not a little to be feared, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, that there are many to be found who are reputed Chriſtians, &amp; yet ſo live, as that if they ſhould depart out of this world in that their evil life, they would find it worſe with them, than with the Jewes. For the Jewes know no other, but that they may Lawfully practiſe Uſury, to get their living. But it is not at all hidden to Chriſtians, that it is ſinful and unlawful to practiſe Uſury; and yet notwithſtanding they do it. Therefore they will be thruſt below the Jews in Hell. And here I would have all thoſe in like manner to be underſtood, who before God are Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and yet would not be accompted, nor called ſo by men. And laſtly, I here note all thoſe, who practice unjuſt morgaging, and hunt for unlawful gains from moneyes, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member truly, that I lived in ſuch a time, when it was exceeding rare, and unuſual to uſe morgaging, and few at that time did practiſe it. And if then any contracts were made with the condition of Re-emption, they were ſincere and ſimple, and according to God; ſo that I my ſelf alſo did permit ſome to make ſuch contracts. But I will tell you
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:151173:60"/> upon what accompt I did it. There came at that time to me certain honeſt men, one of whom ſaid unto me: how do you advice me Sir? I have bought of this man ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Rents for my money upon his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. He alſo is come to me beſeeching me for Gods ſake to do this thing for him; to permit, that writings be made, that may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this condition, that if God enable him to redeem his eſtate, I would permit him for Gods ſake ſo to do. Having heard this, I thus ſaid to the man: tell me prethee, doſt thou eye or intend nothing elſe in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but only to do this purely for Gods ſake? To which he anſwered. Truly, nothing elſe do I mind in this buſineſs. For what elſe ſhould I ſeek, or what elſe ſhould move me, but only that it pitties me that this mans eſtate ſhould be for ever made over to me and my Heirs? otherwiſe I had rather poſſeſs the Goods as my own, according as I purchaſed them. In this manner, Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, I ſometimes heretofore conſented to redemptions; but take notice, I beſeech you, how purely, how ſimply, and according to God, heretofore this was done. But now in theſe our times, we do by our pride and covetouſneſs, ſo pervert, and corrupt theſe redemptions, that for the moſt part they are
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151173:61"/> more then half Uſury before God: the blame of which is almoſt moſtly ours, who are Confeſſors, becauſe we permit ſuch things. Behold, I will tell you, Beloved, into what great miſery in this age we are ſlidden. Not very long ago, there happened a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Citizen to come to me, and ſaid to me: I beſeech you Sir, give me ſome advice in a buſineſs, which I ſhall declare to you. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I, and my Wife, and my Sons have not ſufficient where withal to maintain us according to the faſhion of this age. And therefore I have thoughts to ſell my eſtate upon condition of re-emption: but I would do nothing in it without your advice. If therefore you ſo advice me, I fully purpoſe ſo to do. I made him this anſwer, I will not in the leaſt advice you to it; but rather diſſwade you by all means I can faithfully and ſincerely. He anſwered me, I have not then wherewithal to live according to the cuſtome of theſe times. To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, Take it for certain, if you follow that courſe, you have told me, you will grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly offend God, and will commit ſome mortal ſins. For I would not have you ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that all contracts of buying and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Rents, or Poſſeſſions, in which the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er reſerves power to himſelf, ever to call in
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:151173:61"/> again, when he pleaſeth the principal ſum; (all ſuch contracts I ſay) are not free from uſury: for in all thoſe contracts, in which upon loan any gain is expected, by covenant or principal intention explicitly, with what colour ſoever; notwithſtanding many endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour now a dayes to excuſe it: in all thoſe contracts, I ſay, for the moſt part, there is a mixture of uſury. So therefore; firſt, you will make your ſelf partaker of anothers uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, if without preſſing neceſſity you make uſe of a common Uſurer; or elſe you draw your neighbour, who before uſed it not, to practiſe uſury. Secondly, you incur the guilt of avarice, (which is one of the ſeven capital ſins) whileſt that moves you to do this. Thirdly, alſo you will ſin by pride, whilſt you do this: for this end, that you, and your wife, and your children, may be conformable to the luxury and pomp of the Age, and be like to others. Wherefore, for theſe reaſons, I dare by no means adviſe you to it; but rather, with what faithfulneſs I can, I give you this counſel, That you live contented with your lot, and with thoſe goods which God hath granted you, after the manner of ancient time; and be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to God, who doubtleſs will ſuccour you ſo doing, that you ſhall have what is ſufficient
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:151173:62"/> for you. Certainly, if you acquieſce in this my counſel, and do as I tell you, you ſhall perceive it will be profitable to you, both for body and ſoul. Then ſaid he, I give you thanks, Reverend Sir, for this wholſome counſel, which you have beſtowed on me, which I fully determine to follow, and let paſſe that which I had thought to do. See now Beloved, whither we are fallen. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards I perceived that the ſame honeſt man, the ſame year went to a certain other Doctor who permitted it him, as lawfull: ſo that he ſold all his Eſtate under the forementioned doubtfull condition of Redemption. Plainly 'tis we make for you the way too broad; and yet in truth it is not ſo; but ſtrait is the way which leadeth to life. <note place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> Alas, which is never enough to be bewailed, things are come to that paſſe now a dayes, that there are few affairs among Chriſtian People, which are wholly juſt and ſincere. Alas for grief, how many blinde guides are to be found at this day? And if the blind tumble upon the blind into Hell, both their conditions will be ſo much the worſe. Wherefore, Beloved, it very much concerns you to look to your ſelves: for I fear that the friendſhip of the men of this world, is too dear to many of us <hi>Confeſſors.</hi> I will tell you ſomething of my
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:151173:62"/> ſelf, and I'le ſpeak the ſimple truth; but I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you let no man be ſcandalized thereat. At a certain time it came very importunatly into my mind, that I muſt go beyond the Seas, and expoſe my body to the dangers of death, and muſt preach the Word of God to the Pagans, and try, if by God's help I might be able to convert any of them to the Faith of Chriſt. This will increaſed in me, and waxed ſo ſtrong, that I were now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved even to prepare me for the journey, and did think with my ſelf of the manner, how I might come thither. And when I were carefully taken up with this matter, it fell out on a certain morning, that when I had returned to bed, and was now fallen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, me thought I heard one ſpeaking to me theſe words: Whither do you intend your journey? There is no need to paſs the Seas to Pagans, for you ſhall find many of them here among Chriſtians, who whilſt they bear the Name of Chriſt, live worſe than Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. When therefore you have preached ſo long to theſe, till they attain to a true life, and a life worthy of a Chriſtian; then at laſt take free leave to paſs to the Saracens. This admonition was given me in my ſleep three times, and alwayes in the ſame form of words: from whence it came to paſſe, that
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:151173:63"/> I recalled my mind from contriving to paſſe the Seas.</p>
                     <p>Hence now ſomething ſhould be ſpoken of the Merchants, but I fear that I am too tedious. Notwithſtanding I will ſpeak a few words concerning them. There are ſome Merchants now a dayes, who do get their eſtates by very unjuſt wayes, and ſuch as are exceeding contrary to God, and that by ſo various and diverſe <hi>unjust means,</hi> that I cannot here relate them all. But be ſure of it ye Merchants, whereas ye ſell any thing, in what Country ſoever, the dearer, becauſe of time reſpited for payment, <hi>(dearer I ſay)</hi> than otherwiſe you would have done, if the buyer had paid you ready money; whatever you receive in this caſe above the juſt price, all that extends to uſury before God, ſeeing ye extort that from your neighbours. The ſame is to be thought, whilſt you exchange your money, aſſign, or lend it for a certain term; which when it cometh, ye know what gain is to be allowed you out of every hundred crowns, as for your Intereſt (as you call it) becauſe of the dammage which ye pretend to receive by the forbearance; in the mean time concealing the word Uſury. Alas, what end I pray will there be of your covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? If ye will be wiſe Merchants, why do
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:151173:63"/> ye not rather get eternal riches, <note place="margin">Luk. 16.</note> by making to your ſelves friends of the mammon of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to wit, the poor, whoſe is the Kingdom of Heaven, of whom ye may hold it, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which rich men ſhall not enter, without works of mercy? <hi>Wo unto you</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <note place="margin">Hab. 2.</note> 
                        <hi>which gather together thoſe things which are not your own. How long will ye heap up againſt your ſelves thick clay?</hi> In the mean time indeed, you and your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions may cover over theſe things with a cloak in this world, and defend them by ſome falſe comments; yet they will not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be juſt before God. But when we come into eternity, there every covering will be taken away, and what ever ſhall be unjuſt, will appear to all clearer than the light.</p>
                     <p>But to be briefer, look upon your own ſelves, I beſeech you, ye dealers in the world (for this is chiefly neceſſary for you) and take heed to your ſelves; for very many times in your buying and ſelling ye tell lies, and impoſe upon your neighbour, sby certain ſubtile gloſſes and equivocating words. How ye ſpend alſo Feaſtival days, which ye ought to have in reverence, and obſerve, ye beſt know. Finally, how many cuſtoms and will-wayes are now riſen up, ye are not at all igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. Furthermore, all theſe things, we,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151173:64"/> who receive your confeſſions, ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove: but alas, many of us do diſſemble more than is fitting, and wickedly tolerate you. Truly I fear, that ſome of us receive ſometimes ſome preſents from you, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of them permit and ſuffer you to heap and keep together by any manner of means, as much as would ſuffice an hundred to live on. Which goods, though they ſhould be juſtly got, yet you ought nevertheleſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve thoſe that want out of them, for to that end were they conferred upon you by God. <note place="margin">Luk. 16.</note> Verily that rich man who was cloathed in purple and ſilks, and fared ſumptuouſly every day; when he was dead, he was buried in Hell, for this cauſe doubtleſs, becauſe he kept to himſelf the goods granted to him by God, and uſed them according to the luſt of his nature. And although we read of nothing that he unjuſtly poſſeſſed, or that he took by violence any other mans goods; yet he was compelled to undergo the endleſs tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Hell. Hear now ye Merchants, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold your ſelves I beſeech you, and examine your ſelves: For hardly, as I truly judge, can it be, but where ye gain ſuch great ſums of money, and ſo much ſuperfluous goods, but that ye poſſeſs the ſame with Pride and Covetouſneſs; yea, and with many other
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:151173:64"/> great ſins, which uſually for the moſt part mingle herewith; Which you your ſelves would plainly diſcover, if it were not irkſom to you rightly to ſearch into, and examine the matter. Here by the way, Ile tell you, Beloved, what befell me within theſe five years, if I rightly remember. There came to me a certain Merchant, a very rich man, and entred familiarly into diſcourſe with me, and among other things told me, that there were due to him in a certain forreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, very much, and very great Commodities. I required of him, how it came to paſſe that ſo much was owing to him in a forreign Country? He anſwered, that his Wares were there ſold, and delivered to Chapmen, and that they owed him ſo much. Again, replied I, tell me the truth; if any one would have bought of you thoſe Commodities at ſomewhat a lower price, but yet with ready money, would you have let him had them? Yes, doubtleſs, anſwered he, I would have let him had them, and had rather have had it ſo; that with ready money I might have bought other Commodities. I replied and ſaid, be ſure therefore whatever you receive for reſpiting of time, more than you would have taken in ready money, all that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt. And although it hath not got the name
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151173:65"/> of Uſury among men, yet ſo it is called be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the right and juſt judgment of God. Contrarily, replied he, It is otherwiſe; for this is the manner and cuſtom of all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries to do ſo. I anſwered him, That mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not, neither is it therefore juſt and equal; for you make ſuch will-cuſtoms, and naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty inventions, and have made them; and therefore it is the worſe. Will ye make cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, which are contrary to God, a Law? it will therefore alſo be a cuſtom to deſcend into Hell. Wherefore, as I ſaid before, take it for certain, if you any where whatever, or in any Country whatever, fell any thing dearer, becauſe of time given for payment, than you would have done if they had paid ready money; or, if you get gain for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney lent, becauſe of time given for payment; whatever you thus receive, it is all to be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned among unjuſt and ill-gotten goods; and therefore alſo muſt be reſtored to them from whom it was received, if ever you will be ſaved. When he heard this, he ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, Truly you are a hard man: my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor alwayes permitted me this thing. I anſwered, Your Confeſſor peradventure took your money, and permitted you that, which God himſelf with all his Omnipotency can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not permit you. See here, Beloved, how
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:151173:65"/> pernicious a thing Covetouſneſs is. That rich Merchant thus went from me, not ſo much as in word teſtifying any purpoſe ever of amending his life. Believe me Beloved, it is above all things neceſſary for us all, from our hearts to amend our ſelves, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our evil lives: for we live in too too perilous times; and it is to be feared that yet more perilous times are at hand. But what ſhall I ſay, when as it is told me, there are not wanting ſome who do blame me, as if I did preach too rigidly and ſeverely? But I doubt not conſtantly to affirm, that there is not one of all theſe ſtanding here before me, who would not preach much more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely than I do, if ſo be he had experienced what I have; and that it lay upon him as his duty ordinarily to preach, as it doth on me. And if it would not be too tedious to you, I would tell you ſome things, which would be not a little congruous to this place, and would be profitable for you to hear it. <hi>Then very many of the People altogether with one voice ſaid, Speak aſſuredly Sir, for you ſhall find us patient and benevolous hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</hi> I rehearſe therefore unto you, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, a thing that befell my ſelf. Upon a certain time I ſat alone in a Cell, and when I had began to think of the wonderfull
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:151173:66"/> things of God, and how ſtrange the ſtate of the Church was at this time, how all good order was too much neglected, and went to rack. In the midſt of theſe medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, I heard a certain voice with my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ears, ſpeaking to me, although I ſaw no body at all.</p>
                     <p>But after this manner it ſpake: Ariſe, now you muſt experience ſome things, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you may be enabled ſo much the more certainly to ſpeak the truth openly to your neighbours. And at this laſt word I were deprived of all my ſenſual diſcerning, and being taken into an extaſie, I was in that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rapture permitted to ſee into Purgatory; where I beheld the torments of multitudes of men, (many of which I knew) ſo pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſo intolerably bitter, and ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe puniſhments, and ſorrows ſo intenſe, and fearfull, that no reaſon, no underſtanding is ſufficient to expreſs them. In brief, take it for certain, that I beheld there ſo many, ſo various and divers kinds of torments, in a wonderfull manner painfull, that ſuch a terrour and trembling hath ſeized upon me, that all the natural joyes of this life can in no wiſe make me merry; and if I ſhould live yet an hundred years, I think I ſhould never be merry, except God ſhould make
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:151173:66"/> me ſo by ſome ſupernatural means. But I beſeech you, Beloved, let not any be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at this, that I would relate ſuch things as theſe are unto you. Truly I fear, that ſome peradventure do think, that in divulg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe things, I ſeek glory to my ſelf. But let me aſſure you, I ſeek or wiſh the praiſe of no man, nay nor the wealth of any one for this reaſon: for I am abundantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with thoſe things, which in our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery, according to the cuſtom of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent are provided for me: Nay, I am never without fear, leſt peradventure I ſhould take that which is ſuperfluous, of thoſe things, which are ſet before me in our Hall. And certainly I believe that there is not one here preſent, who, if he had ſeen and experienced thoſe things, which I have ſeen and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced, namely, ſuch horrible and fearfull puniſhments, but would peradventvre have been better contented with a ſmall proviſion and allowance, than I am. Therefore let none of you be ſcandalized at my words fore-ſpoken. In good earneſt I find no other cauſe why God would have me to ſee ſuch things, but becauſe of my ſins and iniquities, that I might both reform my ſelf, and the more boldly ſpeak to others the truth, which I have certainly known; and
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:151173:67"/> in no wiſe flatter their wickedneſſes and ſins. And hence, if I were ſure for this cauſe to be put to death, I ſhould nevertheleſs ſpeak the naked and ſimple truth. Truly, I ſaw ſome in thoſe moſt vehement pains, and was taken with extream admiration, that they ſhould deſire to remain ſo long, in ſo great anguiſh, ſith ſome of them had departed this life many years before, who, whilſt they lived, I did believe were both good and pious; and yet they did undergo in thoſe places of Purgatory ſo great and ineffable puniſhments, that no man can in this life ponder or underſtand them, as they deſerve. Wherefore this, I from my heart do counſel all, that we ſlight not Purgatory; but be ſpeedily converted, and ſeriouſly reform our ſelves. Certainly if you did know, how above meaſure valuable and profitable the preſent time is, you would not eſteem it ſo little, nor ſuffer it to paſſe away ſo fooliſhly; for truly, when we are brought out of this tranſitory time, into things future and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, there exceeding ſpeedy, ſimple, right and rigid judgment paſſeth upon thoſe, who ſuffer this preſent time fooliſhly to paſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. But what ſhall I ſay, Beloved? for if I attempt to ſpeak any thing to you of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Juſtice, that is ſo immeaſurable, ſtrict,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:151173:67"/> and rigid, that I fear ſome of you may take occaſion of deſpair from hence: If contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I would diſcourſe of his infinit mercy, how ready he is to ſhew it to all in this life: I fear on the other hand ſome would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume ſo upon it, that they would live worſe and more fooliſhly, and ſo may admit of ſome ſuch ſin, as (it were to be feared) God would not pardon either here or hereafter. I fear truly, Beloved, leſt I have been too tedious, although many things yet remain to be ſpoken of divers ſorts of men, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers affairs; becauſe that we have gone too far aſtray from the right way. And in truth if I did, laying aſide all things elſe, attend only the duty of Preaching for this whole year, I think I could in no wiſe ſufficiently lay open all our defects and ſins. But when the Lord ſhall order it, I will further ſpeak of this matter. Ariſe now, and ſay the Lords Prayer, with the Angels Salutation.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>After theſe things, it fell out on a certain time, that the Maſter made a journey to a certain Incluſory, in which there abode five Incluſis, which earneſtly entreated him, to preach to them a Sermon of the true and perfect ſecluſe life. To whom he ſaid, that he would willingly do what they deſired, if the Lord ſo ordered it, upon the Lords day
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:151173:68"/> next following. When therefore that Lords<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day was come, there came together to that place a multitude of men, and the Maſter began his Sermon thus.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="sermon">
                  <body>
                     <head>The following Sermon was preached up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lords day of <hi>Sexageſima;</hi> the ſubject of it was this: namely, Why St. <hi>Paul</hi> kept in ſilence his Rapture into the third Heaven ſo many years: That the Gifts of God come by affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, or at leaſt are confirmed by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions. Of a twofold Self-denial, one of Nature, the other of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Laſtly, What belongs to a true Incluſe.</head>
                     <div type="sermon">
                        <epigraph>
                           <q>
                              <p>I knew a man in Chriſt above forty years ago, &amp;c.</p>
                              <bibl>2 Cor. 12.2.</bibl>
                           </q>
                        </epigraph>
                        <p>SAint <hi>Paul,</hi> Beloved, hath delivered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us in his Epiſtles to day a wholſom and neceſſary inſtruction. But becauſe the ſaid Epiſſle is too long, I will not rehearſe to you all of it, but only part of it. The Apoſtle therefore ſaith, ſpeaking of himſelf, <hi>I knew a man in Chriſt above fourteen years ſince,</hi> ſuch a one <hi>(whether in the body, or out of the body, I know not, God knoweth)
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:151173:68"/> taken up even into the third Heaven.</hi> Here my Beloved, take notice, I beſeech you, how the holy Apoſtle kept in ſilence this his Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for full fourteen years together, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would he bring it forth in publick un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til it was permitted him ſo to do by God. <note place="margin">Againſt raſh bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</note> He did not certainly, as ſome men now a dayes, who, when they receive peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſome ſmall grace from God, inſtantly break forth, and tell it others without the permiſſion of God, and declare it ſometimes to ſuch men, as do as little underſtand ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, what it is, or whither it tends, as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; whereby alſo very many times it comes to paſſe, that ſuch Grace is taken away from ſuch like Bablers, and given to another more illuminated, Therefore ſee, my Beloved, that without the permiſſion of God, ye never divulge the gifts, which are conferred upon you by him, being ſure that few are to be found now a dayes, who are endowed with illuminated reaſon or diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And therefore heed is to be taken that the gifts of God be not brought forth ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, and without his licence. Now that it was permitted to S. <hi>Paul</hi> by God, to ſpeak of thoſe things which had hapned to him, it was permitted by God for our warning and neceſſary inſtruction; namely, that if it
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:151173:69"/> ſhould happen that he ſhould infuſe into any one of us his preventing grace, winhout any merit precedent; ſuch a one ſhould not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards be ſhaken with terrour, if he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to be afflicted, even as it uſually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell bleſſed <hi>Paul.</hi> 
                           <note place="margin">To whom the gifts of God do come.</note> Yes verily, it is to be taken for certain, that the gifts of God come by afflictions: but if they come before af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, certain it is that yet they ought to be confirmed and proved by afflictions. When as therefore it is a matter of ſo much nobleneſs and profit to endure adverſity; for that reaſon the Almighty God hath ſuffered ſo heavie afflictions to meet with all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Saints; and for the ſame cauſe he gave leave to the bleſſed Apoſtle to relate to us his afflictions: for he ſaith in this ſame Epiſtle; <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11</note> 
                           <hi>Are they the Ministers of Christ? I ſpeak as a fool, I more: In very many labours, in priſons more abundantly, in ſtripes above meaſure; in deaths frequently: five times of the Jews received I forty ſtripes but one: Thrice was I beaten with rods, once was I ſtoned, thrice I ſuffered ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack; a night and a day I was in the depth of the ſea; in journies often, in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of rivers, in dangers of robbers, in dangers from my kinred, in dangers from the nations, in dangers in the city, in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:151173:69"/> in the deſarts, in dangers in the ſea, in dangers among falſe brethren, in labour and toil, in watchings, in hunger and thirſt, in much fasting, in cold and nakedneſs &amp;c.</hi> Theſe and many other things the bleſſed Apoſtle commemorates in this dayes Epiſtle, by him to have been endured; in reciting of each of which, leſt I ſhould be the more tedious, I will adde only this one, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt he adjoyns, ſaying, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.</note> 
                           <hi>Leſt the Greatneſs of Revelations ſhould lift me up, there was given me a prick of my fleſh, the Angel of Satan, who might buffet me: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of which I beſought the Lord thrice, that it might depart from me: and he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered me, My Grace</hi> (Paul) <hi>is ſufficient for thee: for ſtrength is perfected in weakneſs. VVillingly therefore</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>will I glory in my infirmities, that the vertue of Chriſt may dwell in me.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Now therfore, Beloved, after that St. <hi>Paul,</hi> a veſſel of Election, hath in this his Epiſtle abundantly proved unto us, how great the profit of Afflictions is; truly it deſerves, that we ſhould give credit to ſo great an Apoſtle, and imitate and follow him. Yea, truly, it cannot be, that ever we ſhould attain to a praiſe-worthy and fruitful life, except we willingly renounce the pleaſures of Nature.
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:151173:70"/>
                           <note place="margin">What it is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Nature.</note> Becauſe to renounce Nature, is nothing elſe but voluntarily to refuſe and deny all things in which Nature is delighted; thoſe things only excepted, which upon a rational ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count are neceſſary to the ſuſtentation of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; which ſhall be ſuch things as may be helpful to us in the ſervice of God, and in the coming to God: all other things are to be forſaken for God's ſake. Neither indeed can any one experience, or receive the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour ſweetneſs of God, except he bid <hi>adeu</hi> to the ſweetneſs of fading things, and to the inclination and pleaſure of the ſenſes. And hence the Apoſtle ſaith, <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
                           <hi>If ye will live after the fleſh, ye ſhall die: but if by the Spirit ye ſhall mortifie the deeds of the fleſh, ye ſhall live.</hi> Here let us contemplate, and (to the utmoſt of our power) follow the every way lovely example of our Lord and Saviour, ſo as the ſame Apoſtle doth admoniſh: <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> 
                           <hi>Put off</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the old man, and put on our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And furthermore, there is yet another much more noble and excellent Self-denial, than that is by which we deny Nature; <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> and that is, when willingly we renounce the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; which how it is done, I would have you mark. After that the Spirit hath whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tamed the fleſh, and reduced it to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:151173:70"/> and now is climed above all caducal and ſlippery things; then it taketh, as it were, a leap into everlaſting good things themſelves, which doubtleſs are much more delightfull to it, both in taſt and fruition, than natural delights were before. When therefore any one cometh to taſt, and enjoy thoſe excellent higheſt goods, he ought then no leſſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce thoſe delights and affluences of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, than before he was fain to do thoſe of Nature; ſo as he may know how to leave to God his gifts and operations, according to his will and pleaſure. This Renunciation alſo is not a little difficult at the beginning, to them who have taſted God according to the deliciouſneſs of Spirit. This ſame Renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation is called <hi>Poverty of Spirit,</hi> of which the Lord ſpeaketh, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed are the Poor in Spirit, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Yea verily, oft-times it falls out that ſome come to that paſſe, that they exceeding ſubtilly ſnatch and draw what ever ſhineth and ſavoureth in them. to themſelves, into their ground, into their will and arbitrement, neither leave themſelves to God by way of mortification: But whoever are thus, they doubtleſs uſe the grace and gifts of God too too unfruitfully; the reaſon of which is, that when it is not hidden to God, that unleſs he
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:151173:71"/> infuſe into them light and ſavour, they will quickly depart from him; therefore he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains them with ſome ſweet leſſer comforts, leſt they ſhould altogether forſake him; Such like men are as yet exceeding frail &amp; weak; becauſe they are ſuch as are full of ſelf-will, and love and imbrace the ſhadow inſtead of the thing it ſelf: who have alſo this fault, That though they are moſtly outward and external, yet they think themſelves after a manner to be of us: but they are too much deceived in their opinion.</p>
                        <p>Furthermore, they that from the bottom or ground, reſign and offer themſelves to God, and who do receive from him ſweet and bitter alike; who, laſtly, though the influence of light and ſavour be withdrawn from them, do not in any wiſe therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from God; theſe are the true internal ones.</p>
                        <p>Verily, whoever after this manner, now ſpoken of, have denied themſelves, and with a willing mind have penetrated through the ſweetneſſes, aſwell of Spirit as of Nature, and have got above them; theſe certainly have made a profitable and fruitful thorow pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, and have penetrated through more than can be ſpoken. But afterwards ſuch have need of very much vigilancy and watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:151173:71"/> whereby alwayes they muſt diligently obſerve themſelves, be circumſpect and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that they may ever perſevere in very great humility: For their helliſh enemies ceaſe not then, but continually endeavour by all means they can to draw them back.</p>
                        <p>Believe me, Beloved, profound reſignation, and voluntary denial of our ſelves through our whole nature, is a certain good begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, if ſo be it be joyned with true humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: Even as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Dearly Beloved, humble your ſelves under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt you in the time of viſitation.</hi> And, O that we could learn, how we might attain to true ſubjection of ſpirit in profound humility, that when God doth withdraw from us ſenſible Grace, we may be able eaſily to reſign it to him, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain our appetite or deſire, ſo as not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to cover it. This is that which St. <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius</hi> ſaith, When God makes his abode ſenſibly in my ſoul, I am filled with ſuch joy, and it is ſo well with me, that if he ſhould beſtow upon me ſuch authority, that all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that very hour ſhould no leſſe obey me than himſelf, it would not go ſo wel with me, as it doth by his preſence only: But when his ſenſible preſence is withdrawn from me, (I confeſs) then ſome deſire of it layes hold
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:151173:72"/> on me: But when that happens to me, my weakneſs ſurely is the cauſe of it; Seeing <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, that in all the Works of God we ought to have reſt and peace. Behold that breathing and languiſhing deſire holy <hi>Dionyſius</hi> accounts his weakneſs: Why ſo? but becauſe the holy man clearly underſtood that himſelf was not as yet fully reſigned to God, when as he ſo deſired the preſence of God; ſeeing it is the greateſt reſignation, to reſign our ſelves to deſertion, and in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of deſertion to be reſigned: Which thing doth chiefly belong to them, who have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly experienced the ſweetneſs of God.</p>
                        <p>It behoveth us truly, Beloved, ſo manfully to ſtrive, that we may be made ſo prudent in God, that we may be able, having di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine aſſiſtance, to tranſcend and penetrate all creatures, untill we attain unto God himſelf. There now we are taught in the Holy Ghoſt to tread upon, by our reaſon, and get above all natural things, that we may be able with St. <hi>Augustine,</hi> to ſay, <hi>All creatures are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us an high-way unto God.</hi> So as what ever we happen to ſee or hear, of what nature ſoever it be, we may have the skill to bend all to our own uſe, and turn it to the beſt, and to draw ſome good out of it. Certainly a Chriſtian ought by his reaſon ſo oft and ſo
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:151173:72"/> humbly to exerciſe himſelf, and ſo often to penetrate all creatures, until he hath loſt all created things; and he ſhould ſo ſtrongly and manfully, and that not once, but many times, abſtract himſelf from all things, until he find God alone the joy of his ſoul, and the beloved of his heart; of whom the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtle ſpeaks, when he ſaith, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.</note> 
                           <hi>Who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hereth to God, is one Spirit.</hi> In which tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, the ſpirit of ſuch a one is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and is made one with the one. If any one in this matter would venture himſelf, and perfectly renounce both himſelf and all creatures, he ſurely would by Gods help, or by the power of God, overcome all things; which thing <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth, where he ſaith, <note place="margin">Philip. 4.</note> 
                           <hi>I can do all things in him that ſtrengthneth me.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Go to now, Beloved, make ſpeed, be do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, haſten, learn to live, being alſo ſure that a man may in this preſent time attain to that condition, that he may experience ſo immenſe ſupernatural joy, ſuch as all creatures cannot afford even until Doomſ-day.</p>
                        <p>Laſtly, Come on then, and let us all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to learn, by what means we may be made true Worſhippers, <note place="margin">John 4.</note> 
                           <hi>worſhipping the Father in Spirit and Truth.</hi> But I fear leſt I am too tedious, ſith thoſe Incluſes have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:151173:73"/> me, that I would declare unto them, what is the duty of a true Incluſe: <note place="margin">What the Duty of Incluſis is</note> And now this I ſhall diſpatch in a few words, and will tell what manner of one every true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſe ought to be: It belongs therefore to every Incluſe, that ſhe be ſimple, and both in mind and body, that is, both inwardly and outwardly to be an Incluſe. It doth not become her to look out at the windows, and be inquiſitive what is, or what hath been tranſacted here or there; it is meet that ſhe ſhould lead ſo pure, ſo abſtracted a life, that if ſhe ſhould pour forth prayers for all the Souls that are detained in places of Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; ſhe may be found worthy, ſufficient, and able to free them all from thence. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Incluſory life, is no ſmall matter: It behoveth plainly an Incluſe, ſo ſincerely and purely to live, that ſhe may be able to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain all that of God, which the Univerſal hely Church, by the ſeven told grace of the Holy Ghoſt, doth obtain: If ſhe do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, ſhe is not a true Incluſe. She ought alſo to lead ſuch a life, that if all Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Laws were taken away, it might not at all prejudice her to God-ward: <note place="margin">The cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ſtate of Inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> But alas! things are now come to that paſs, that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſes entertain Gueſts in the evening, and in the morning adminiſter to them many
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:151173:73"/> things: which is not the Office of Incluſes, but of Hoſpitallers.</p>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Incluſes muſt keep ſilence.</note> And moreover, it belongs to an Incluſe, diligently to obſerve ſilence, except only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reaſonable and real neceſſity; as alſo purely and earneſtly to pray. It belongs not to her to perform the office of an Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taller, and to diſcourſe with men; but this rather is her duty, that ſhe perpetually per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſo reſolutely and immovably in true and divine reſignation, that ſhe may be able, even with a ſenſible delight, and joyful conſent, alwaies to wait the ſenſible preſence of God, and nevertheleſs perſevere faithful unto him, and therewith to renounce all creatures for his ſake.</p>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">To whom it belongs to ſerve the Poor.</note> But now you may hear ſome Incluſes ſay, That it is their duty to exerciſe themſelves in vertues towards their neighbours; but ſuch ought to have betaken themſelves not to an Incluſory, but to an Hoſpital rather, and there humbly exerciſe themſelves about the Members of Chriſt, which then had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belonged to them as their office; for this they ought faithfully to do, who live in Hoſpitals.</p>
                        <p>Again, others ſay, I muſt ſerve and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour my neighbours for God's ſake. But neither is this the duty of a true Incluſe: for
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:151173:74"/> if ſhe would more narrowly look into it, ſhe would ſurely finde, how that ſecretly it doth fight againſt her purpoſe. Every true Inlcuſe ought to lead ſo pure, ſo abſolute a life, ſo free and ſo abſtracted from all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that her merits may be able to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and help all univerſally, that are inrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led under the Name of Chriſt.</p>
                        <p>But yet there are others, which ſay they are of ſo weak and frail a nature, that it is neceſſary for them, that they ſhould relieve themſelves, by diſcourſing with men, and by that means ſuccour their infirmity. O ſuch miſerable Incluſes! how wholly are they deceived by the counſel of the malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant one? Take it for certain, Beloved, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſeeks any thing elſe in an Incluſory, than for Gods ſake willingly to ſuffer, ſuch a one doth unadviſedly betake her ſelf thereto.</p>
                        <p>Now ſome may be found, who enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Incluſory, that in it they may be fed by Alms with peace and eaſe; which Alms notwithſtanding they would but very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly beg as exiles, in a deſpicable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner openly in the ſtreets: but as many as are after this manner, do raſhly take to themſelves the name of Incluſes (<hi>alias</hi> pure Nuns:) and it would be much better for their ſouls, that they ſhould lie as Exiles in
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:151173:74"/> the high-way, in ſuch a plight as might move the minds of all paſſengers to pitty. But when any Incluſe enters into an Inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory, ſhe ought to offer her ſelf purely, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nakedly, and voluntarily to Chriſt, for to undergo the Croſſe for all men; bearing in mind thoſe words, which Chriſt ſpake upon the Croſſe, <note place="margin">Mat. 27.</note> 
                           <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> That bleſſed and venerable <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> was a true Incluſe; ſeeing ſhe of her own accord renounced all the comfort of creatures. Certainly, God the Father Almighty ſent his Son unto the Earth, and would have him take upon him humane nature, that in it he might ſuffer; and yet notwithſtanding we alwayes flie ſuffering. But whatever we can do, it is moſt certain, if we will take the nearer way, and ſooner, and more ſubtily penetrate all things; that cannot otherwiſe be done, than by following the moſt true Example of our Lord and Saviour, by ſuffering at leaſt in ſome meaſure.</p>
                        <p>And nevertheleſs, which here I bring for our comfort: Truly God the heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is not ſo hard and ſevere towards us, as he hath been towards his only Son. For verily, if we with our whole ſtrength offer our ſelves to God for to ſuffer, ſo as that
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:151173:75"/> we become willing of our own accord, and freely to undergo, whatever pleaſeth him we ſhould bear, neither in the time of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction depart from him, neither do fly from afflictions when they meet us: When he ſhall take notice of this, he will the more ſpeedily, when he ſhall ſee time, take away from us all afflictions, and will fill us with his divine and ſupernatural, pleaſant and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible conſolation; which truly to whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it happens, namely that he experience in himſelf this feſtival and pleaſant Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſuch a one afterwards reliſhes no earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feſtival. He is not made joyful like com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon men at the ſolemnity of a Maſſe, nor at the feaſt of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> or of <hi>Penticoſt,</hi> nor finally at any other feaſt. This huge internal feaſt only, namely, whilſt the Omnipotent God cometh unto him with his ſupernatural and preſent Grace in Jubilee and Triumph; this inward feaſt (I ſay) doth fill him with abundant joy. And that at what time of the year ſoever it be tranſacted in him, at the ſame time all the aforeſaid Solemnities and Feſtivals are together celebrated and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled. Wherefore (dearly Beloved) we ought willingly to bear whatever adverſity ſhall happen unto us: for whoever he be that doth by ſufferings attain to this ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:151173:75"/> and pleaſant Solemnity, this man becomes thereby exceeding prudent, eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, and well compoſed, and obtaineth ſo great a wiſdom by the influence of the Holy Ghoſt, that he doth abundantly underſtand what belongs to him to do, and what to leave undone. Then certainly all his in him are made fruitful, yet he then hath nothing at all of himſelf: but alwayes perſevering in great humility, ſuppoſeth himſelf an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſervant, and evermore keepeth himſelf in a certain filial and amorous fear; neither feareth any thing elſe, but leſt he ſhould not fully ſatisfie the beloved of his heart, his moſt loving Father. In this ſtate, (that is) when he attaineth thus far, all his own private inſtitutions, and cuſtoms of his own will, that is, ſuch as are taken up of himſelf, fall off, and his converſation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh ſimply, truly Chriſtian, and erect to heavenly things. In the mean time, he is nevertheleſs unknown to all men, except one of the ſame life, who hath experienced the ſame grace, and ſolemnity.</p>
                        <p>God Almighty grant, that we may learn by afflictions to endure, and by ſufferings, merit to attain unto this ſupernatural, joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and happy ſolemnity, the eternal Truth it ſelf, our Lord Jeſus Chriſt bringing us to
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:151173:76"/> it, who, with the Father and Holy Ghoſt, liveth and reigneth, one God, throughout all Ages of Ages.</p>
                        <closer>Amen.</closer>
                     </div>
                     <div type="institutions">
                        <head>Three certain excellent Inſtitutions.</head>
                        <p>VVHoſoever thou art who at any time haſt a deſire to attain unto God, and unto the moſt excellent ſtate, which in this life can be obtained, it will concern thee ſtudiouſly to obſerve theſe three things which I do add.</p>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <label>1.</label> The firſt is, That in all things thou aim at God, and the honour of God, and not thy own, but chiefly at his will, &amp; not thy own.</item>
                           <item>
                              <label>2,</label> The ſecond is, That in all thy doings and turnings forth, thou ſtudiouſly obſerve thy ſelf, and take diligent notice of thy bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs nothingneſs, and attend with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual diligence, what-ever thou be about, what is doing in thee; and laſtly, have an eye alwayes upon thy own ground.</item>
                           <item>
                              <label>3.</label> The third is, That by no means thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude thy ſelf into thoſe things which are not committed to thee, but let all things alone in their own ſtate and order. Let thoſe things that are good, be good. But the evil judge thou not, but rather being turned into thine ground, there perſevere, diligently and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulouſly
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:151173:76"/> hearkning to the voice of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, exhorting thee that thou abide in him conſtantly, even to the end.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                     <div type="observations">
                        <head>Whoſoever ſhall obſerve theſe two things following, ſhal attain to great matters.</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <label>1.</label> FIrſt, Let him be both inwardly and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in Truth, and from his very ground and bottom and not in words only, little and abject: Let him be (I ſay) in his whole underſtanding, in his ground, and in his own eyes, without any diſſimulation, wholly little and nothing.</item>
                           <item>
                              <label>2.</label> But, ſecondly, Let him be endowed with the love of God, not that ſenſual, which we call Love, but eſſential; that is, that he do inwardly in his ground purely intend God. Wherefore every one ought for this cauſe to be naked and freed from all ſelf animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, underſtanding, and ſenſuality; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God Almighty is naked and free, ſo thereby the Spirit may be fitted and prepared for his pure and naked eſſence: for ſo it is neceſſary that the ſoul be naked and empty, that it may be capable of his ſecret miſteries. Wherefore there is a neceſſity that every one endeavor to cut off all thoſe things, in which he findeth any thing of Self.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:151173:77"/>
               <head>Of the <hi>DEATH</hi> of the <hi>MASTER,</hi> and how after his Departure he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to his Friend the <hi>LAYICK,</hi> giving him an account of his ſevere and horrible departure out of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; declaring that he endured that inſtead of his Purgatory: and alſo aſſuring him of that huge Joy, and everlaſting Felicity, which he had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from God by means of his whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Doctrine.</head>
               <p>HEre we muſt by no means let paſſe, how the oft before-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Maſter, did daily make proficiency in a true, humble, and ſpiritual life, and encreaſed very much in vertue; Yea verily, he was made ſo pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the grace of God, that whatever was to be done in that City or Country where he dwelt, whether it had been Spiritual or Secular, all much deſired to make uſe of his Counſel and Wiſdom, becauſe he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to them, and they had confidence
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:151173:77"/> in him, and puttruſt in him, and did obey his counſels. He made alſo very many Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, as well to Secular as Spiritual men, after the form of thoſe which we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready above recited. And when he had laudably finiſhed nine years in this ſo profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and fruitful life, and (as it is ſaid) was acceptable and dear unto all in all that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and Town. Theſe nine years being fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, it pleaſed the moſt high God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive unto himſelf this his Servant and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Friend, and no longer to leave him in this exile. And becauſe he had decreed to tranſlate him to the celeſtial Manſions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Purgatory, he ſuffered him to fall into grievous and laſting pain and ſickneſs of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſo that he lay for twenty weeks ſick of a Palſie, and ſuffered very ſharp torments.</p>
               <p>When twenty weeks were now expired, he by Divine Grace underſtood not obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that within a few dayes he ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part this world, and that God would put an end to his torments.</p>
               <p>Knowing this, he deſired his ſervants that they would take care to bring his Layick unto him, and that they ſhould acquaint him with his approach and departure, and that he had no ſmall deſire to have him preſent
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:151173:78"/> with him when he died. Without delay, when the Layick knew hereof, obeying the Maſter, he came to him ſpeedily; and being very familiarly received, he enquired how it was with him? To whom the Maſter an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, Truly I think that that day is not very far off, wherein the Lord will take me out of this world. Wherefore you may know that it will be very acceptable to me, and no leſſe comfortable, if you will vouchſafe your preſence with me when I die. But, ſaith he, I would entreat you, that you will take thoſe Paper Books, in which you ſhall find diligently written all whatever hath for a long time been ſpoken or tranſacted between us: There is alſo ſomething of my Life, ſome things which God vouchſafed to work by me, his miſerable and unworthy Servant. And, if you ſhall ſee fit, and the Lord grant leave, compile them all into one little Book.</p>
               <p>To theſe things the Layick gave this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: Behold, Sir, I have by me five of your Sermons, which I writ from your mouth: if therefore you think fit, I will put them in among your other Writings, that of them all one little Volumn may be put forth under your Name.</p>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:151173:78"/>
               <p>To whom the Maſter anſwered; I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat and beſeech you (dear ſon) with as much love as I am able, That you put not out any thing for my ſake, nor under my name. Neither indeed are they mine, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would I they ſhould be known either in my life, or after my death. But they are all Gods, who vouchſafed to do them by me, a miſerable wretch. But yet if you do think that it may be profitable to my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and make for their edification, to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh thoſe things, I am not againſt it, but that they may be ſet forth, only with this caution, that you mention not me, or my name. But you may write after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, (to wit) <hi>The Master ſaid, or did this or that,</hi> alwayes concealing my name. But be careful of this, that when you have compiled this Book, you deliver it to no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in this City to read, leſt peradventure they ſhould apprehend it to be mine: but rather carry it away with you into your Country.</p>
               <p>Finally, the Maſter had many other good diſcourſes with his Layick for eleven dayes together, even to the hour wherein he gave up the ghoſt.</p>
               <p>When that hour was come, he ſaid thus
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:151173:79"/> to he Layick: I would fain (dear ſon) have on your part your conſent, That if it ſhall pleaſe God, I may return unto you in ſpirit after my Death. To whom the Layick anſwered, If it ſhall (ſaid he) ſeem good unto God, I ſhall like it well that his will may be done in this matter.</p>
               <p>Moreover, when the Maſter was even at the point of death, falling into an Agony, he expreſſed ſuch horrible and fearful geſtures, that his Brethren, and as many as were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, from the ſight of thoſe geſtures, fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to no ſmall fear, affright and ſorrow. And ſo at laſt he ended his laſt hour, as much as can be gathered from external ſigns, with great horror. And when he was now dead, almoſt all the City were moved, becauſe he was exceeding dear to them all univerſally.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, when as ſome of that place had taken notice how familiarly the (oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned) Layick ſtuck to him to the laſt, they went about to honour him, and invite him to their feaſts. But when he perceived this, he preſently fled from the City into his own Country. Being onward upon his jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and travelling now upon the third day, about Sun-ſet he came to a certain Village; And becauſe he could not farther travel by
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:151173:79"/> reaſon it began to be dark, neither could find in that Village any publick Inn, he requeſted a certain honeſt man, whom by chance he met in the way, to lodge him and his ſervant, and bid him take of him what he pleaſed. To whom the man anſwered, that he was ready with a willing mind to do what he deſired, if he would accept of ſuch enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment as he could make him: and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly took them in to lodge them: he lodged the Layick after the beſt faſhion he could, but brought his ſervant into a barn upon ſtraw. After they were layen down, the Layick being awake in the night, heard a kind of ſlender voice near him, yet could ſee nothing: thereby he began to be a little affrighted. Then the voice ſpeak to him thus: <hi>Fear not, dear ſon, for I am the Maſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the Layick heard this, he ſaid: I would very willingly know of you, Sir, if at leaſt it be the will of the Lord, how it is with you, and what was the cauſe, that, as far as we could perceive, you finiſhed your life ſo horribly and fearfully? Verily ſome of your Brethren began, as it were, to doubt of you; and truly I fear leſt your ſevere end hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended ſome of them.</p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:151173:80"/>
               <p>To which the voice of the Maſter anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thus: <hi>I will even now open thoſe things to you. Be certain it was ſo decreed of God, that my ſoul aſſoon as it was gone out of my body, ſhould be received by the holy Angels, and by them be defended from the Devils, that they ſhould bring me no further trouble, nor that I ſhould any more ſee them, nor have any thing more to do with them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; And therefore it behoved me to ſhut up my life with ſo fearful an end, and to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo it inſtead of Purgatory. And in truth the malignant ſpirits did bind me faſt with ſo great perplexities, and did aſſault me with ſuch ſubtile and crafty falacies and deceits, that I thought I ſhould have utterly deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And if my voice had not been taken away, I had ſent forth ſuch cryes, that it had been wonderfull to have ſeen my calamity; hence might my Agony which my Brethren did diſcern, have been taken notice of. But God Almighty rendered me a plentiful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for that pain and torment: for, as ſoon as my ſoul was gone out of my body, it was received by the holy Angels, who brought it into Paradiſe, telling me that there I muſt wait five dayes without fear or care; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fear that the Devil ſhould henceforth
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:151173:80"/> do me any miſchief; and finally, that I ſhould undergo no more labour: only I ſhould want for thoſe five dayes the glorious ſociety of the heavenly Inhabitants; which being performed, I ſhould be wholly clean, and that then they would return with joy, and bring me with great exaltation into ineſtimable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be ended joyes. More than this (dear ſon) enquire nothing of me, for I have now told you what-ever I can tell you; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have I any licence to adde any thing further; But I beſeech my God that he would bleſſe you, and that he would be your eternal rewarder in everlasting joyes, for that faithful Inſtruction and wholſom Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel you gave me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the Layick ſaid, I beſeech you my honored Maſter, when you ſhall come unto God, earneſtly intercede with him for me. After that, whatever the Laick did either ask or ſpeak, it was in vain, neither could he get ſo much as one anſwer more from him. Which when he perceived, he endeavoured as much as he could to take a little reſt, but in vain, for he could not ſleep one wink; and ſo lay awake, impatiently expecting day. Day breaking, he took his Pen and diligently wrote to the Prior and Brethren of
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:151173:81" rendition="simple:additions"/> the dead Maſter, how he had appeared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and all his words he had ſpoke to him.</p>
               <p>The eternal Truth, our Lord JESUS CHRIST, grant to us, that we may conform our ſelves to his lovely and dilectable Image, and follow it to our utmoſt power, to his praiſe and glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>To God Almighty thanks.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151173:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
